好的，我想我们开始了，
Alright, I want we get started,
人们想再次打开摄像机，
you know people want to turn on the camera again
它可以很好地创造班级氛围，
or well it be great used to create sort of class atmosphere,
这是我们能做的最好的。
it's the best we can.
好的，这是，
Okay, so this is,
今天我们要讨论这篇论文，
we're going to talk today about this paper,
使用用高级语言编写 UNIX 内核的好处和成本，
you know the benefits and cost of writing a UNIX kernel in a high-level language,
这篇论文编写部分原因是因为 6.S081 或 6.828 ，
you know, this is basically paper that was partly written because of 6.S081 or 6.828,
这篇论文是由我们编写的，
and there's the paper that you know we've written,
Robert 和我，
you know Robert and I,
但主要人物是 Cody Cutler ，
and that the main person was a main lead was Cody Cutler,
他在这门课上当过很多次助教。
who was a TA this class many many times.
这总是有一点，
It's always a little bit,
我不是特别喜欢
you know I don't really enjoy
谈论我们自己编写的论文，
actually particularly talking about papers that we worked on ourselves,
但是这篇论文基本上来自 6.S081 或 6.828 ，
but you know this paper came about basically 6.S081 or 6.828,
所以这次我要用一些幻灯片，
and so I'm gonna use some slides this time
而不是在白板上书写。
instead of actually writing on a whiteboard.
所以这篇论文的真正来源就是这个问题，
And so really the source of this paper is this question
应该用什么语言编写内核。
in what language should you write a kernel.
这是你们很多人都问过的问题，
And this is a question that many, many of you asked
在过去的 6.828 毕业生中问了很多次，
where you know students in the past 6.828 graduate asked many many many times,
因为你的操作系统或内核中有 bug ，
apparently you know because you know you have bugs in the operating system or your kernel
你会说，如果我使用另一种语言编写，
and you're like well, if I had written this other language,
也许我就不会有那些 bug 了。
then you know maybe I would not have those bugs.
所以这是一个经常出现的问题，
So this is a question that often comes about
事实上，在整个操作系统社区中，
and it turns out you know in the operating system community at large,
这是一个争论不休的问题，
you know this is a hotly debated question,
但事实并不多，你可以进行任何知情的讨论。
but not that many facts, you could actually make a sort of any informed discussion.
我们将在这节课结束时看到，
And what we'll see at this at the end of this lecture,
在课程中或你读论文时，
during this lecture or you as you read the paper,
我知道我们对这个问题没有明确的答案，
I know we don't really have a crisp answer to this question,
但是我们这篇论文贡献了很多数据，
but we have sort of this paper contributes you know a bunch of data,
可以让你有更深入的讨论，
that you know allows you to have a little bit more of an in-depth discussion
关于什么是内核的好的编程语言。
about what is a good programming language for the kernel.
这就是这篇论文的原创之处，
So that was really the original of this paper,
基本上这篇论文的来源就是你们。
and and so we're, and the source you know of this paper is basically you guys.
那么，为了回答这个问题，
So, try to answer the question,
我们编写了一个新的内核，
we wrote a new kernel,
并且我们用具有自动内存管理的语言，
and we did it in the language with automatic memory management
这意味着有垃圾收集器，
that means with garbage collector,
所以你不需要调用 free ，
so you don't actually have to call free,
可以避免一类 bug ，
you know and avoid a class bugs,
这是高级语言通常具有的属性之一，
so that's one of the properties at a high level language typically has,
所以，我们希望选择一种具有这种特性的语言，
and so we wanted to have picked a language that has that,
我们基本上遵循了传统的 Unix 结构，
and we followed basically traditional monolithic Unix organization,
我们可以做一个公平的比较。
we could do a fair comparison.
在某种程度上，你可以认为我们构建的是类似于 xv6 的东西，
And in fact some way you could think about what we built is something like xv6,
功能更多，性能更高。
much much more, more features and more high performance.
我的意思是，正如你知道的，
I mean, as you know,
xv6 有各种慢性算法或线性搜索、类型算法，
xv6 has all kinds of chronic algorithms or linear search, type algorithms,
当然，如果你想实现高性能，
and of course if you want to achieve high performance,
你不能有这些。
you can't have those.
所以，这就是论文的来源，
And so that was the original, this paper in the original,
为什么我们构建了 Biscuit 试图回答这个问题，
why we built Biscuit trying to answer that question
或者至少给我们一些启示。
or at least shed some light.
首先，我要讨论一下更一般的背景，
First, I'm going to talk a little bit about sort of more general background,
我通过电子邮件得到很多问题，
I got a lot of questions over email,
我们正试图获得更多的背景信息，
we're trying to get a little bit more context,
然后我会更详细地讨论 Biscuit ，
and then I will dive into Biscuit in more more detail,
任何时间都可以随意提出问题，
feel free to jump in with questions in any particular point of time,
正如你所知道的，这篇论文的动机是你们提出的问题，
here as you know this paper was motivated by questions you asked,
所以，请继续问问题。
and so you know please please ask keep asking questions.
所以，正如你可以做的那样，
So, as you can just do,
这篇论文的设置是很多内核都是用 C 语言写的，
sort of the setting of this paper is a lot of kernels are written in C,
xv6 是用 C 语言写的，你使用 C 语言编写程序，
and you know xv6 is written in C, you're programming in C,
你在桌面或手机上看到的大多数流行内核都是用 C 语言编写的，
but most popular kernels that you see on your desktop or your phone are written in C,
Windows Linux 以及所有各种形式的 BSD 。
Windows Linux Linux to all the various forms of BSDs.
用 C 语言编写的原因是，
And, and the reason the written or written in C is that,
C 提供了很多控制，正如你在实验中看到的，
C provides a lot of control as you've seen in the labs,
完全控制内存分配和释放，
yeah, complete control for memory allocation and freeing,
几乎没有隐式代码，
there's almost no implicit code,
你几乎可以想象，当你阅读 C 代码的时候，
you know you can almost imagine when you're reading the C code,
对应的 RISC-V 指令是什么，
what the corresponding RISC-V instructions are,
你可以直接访问内存，
you have direct access to memory,
你可以读写 PTE 位或者设备寄存器，您知道您知道的PTE位或设备的寄存器，
you can read or write you know the PTE bits you know or the register of a devices,
而且 C 语言本身有很少的依赖，
and you know C itself [] very few dependencies,
你并不需要很大的运行时，
you know there's no large runtime that you actually have to have,
为了能够运行 C 程序，
to be able to run a C program,
你几乎可以直接在裸硬件上运行。
you can almost run almost immediately on bare hareware.
你已经看到一旦 xv6 启动，
And you've seen that once xv6 boots,
先是几行汇编代码，
you know it's basically a few lines of assembly
然后你就是在运行 C 代码。
and then basically you're running C code.
但是这些都是 C 语言优点，
But there are all the good virtues of C
也是我们非常喜欢 C 的一个原因。
and one reason that we like C a lot.
但是 C 也有一些缺点，
But C also has some downsides,
在过去的几十年里已经被证明了，
you know it has been proven over the last few decades,
写安全的 C 代码很难，
that writing security C code is difficult,
有几种类型的 bug ，经常会被利用，
you know there are types of bugs that can, you can often be exploited
无论是缓冲区溢出，
whether it is buffer overruns,
这可能是在过去最广为人知的问题，
which are probably the most well-known one you're writing behind the past,
一个数组绑定，或者你正在堆下面写，
an array bound or you're writing you know below your stack,
use-after-free bug ，你释放了内存，但是它仍在使用，
use-after-free bugs, you know where you know the free of memory, but it's still in use,
所以当有人在上面乱写的时候，
and so when somebody scribbles on it
在上面乱写一些不好的东西，
and you know scribble something bad on it,
通常情况下，线程共享内存时，
and generally you know when threads are sharing memory
很难决定哪些内存可以释放。
is typically difficult to decide you know what actually memory can be freed.
有些 bug ，并不会真的出现在那里，
Some of these bugs, you know don't really show up that,
一些 bug 明确地体现在 xv6 中，一些较少，
you know some of the bug manifest itself explicitly xv6, some less,
xv6 的动态内存分配非常少，
so you know, you know xv6 very little dynamic memory allocation,
你几乎是已经预先分配好了，
you're almost after being sort of pre allocated [right up front],
缓冲区溢出通常会出现释放 bug 。
a buffer overruns usually have free bugs do show up.
事实上，如果你看一看 CVEs ，
So, in fact you know if you look at CVEs,
有一个网站，
you know these are you know there's a website
有一个组织保持控制，
where there's an organization that keeps control,
检查和记录所有安全漏洞，
that checks and keeps a record of all of the security exploits,
调查一下，你会发现，在 2017 年我们做这篇论文的时候，
and investigate that you'll find that in 2017 when we were doing this paper,
有 40 个 Linux 内核 bug ，
that there were 40 Linux kernel bugs,
会导致攻击者完全控制机器。
that can actually lead to an attacker running take complete control over the machine.
显然，那些是严重的 bug ，
Clearly, you know those are serious bugs
这些 bug 来自于缓冲区溢出，
and those bugs came out of buffer overruns
以及其他类型的内存安全 bug 。
and other types of memory safety bugs.
所以这太糟糕了，
So you know it's sort of too bad,
如果你用 C 语言写代码，
you know that if you write code in C,
很难做到，
you know that actually is hard,
即使是专业人士也很难做到这一点。
even for people that do that professionally and to actually get this right.
当然，我相信你在实验里见过这个，
And of course you know, I'm sure you've seen this in the lab,
也许，我记得在 Piazza 上的一些问题，
you know probably certainly I remember from some of the the Piazza questions,
你们遇到 use-after-free bug 的次数，
you know the number if you run into use-after-free bugs,
特别是在写入时复制实验里，
you know in particular in the copy-on-write lab,
它们出现了很多次。
they showed up a bunch of times.
所以，高级语言吸引人的一个原因是，
So yeah so, one reason that a high-level language would be attractive is that,
高级语言提供了内存安全，
a high-level language that provides memory safety,
所以，所有 CVE 披露的 bug ，
and so all these bugs that CVE exploits
我在上一张幻灯片中提到的，
that I mentioned on the previous slide
将会是不可能的，
would not be would not be possible,
如果它们发生了，
you know could use you know they if they happen,
它们要么会导致 panic ，
they either would result in a panic,
因为运行时会说，
you know, because you know the runtime which would say,
你要写的东西已经不在了，你不能那样做，
like, oh you're writing passed away, you can't do that,
或者根本不能表现出来，
or you know you just couldn't manifest itself at all,
因为语言不会允许你编写这样的代码。
because the language wouldn't allow you to write that kind of code.
高级语言当然还有其他好处，
So there are of course other benefits to a high-level language,
这门课上的学生也经常提到，
you know which often is also mentioned you know by you know students in this class,
当他们在做实验时，
when they're doing labs,
除了类型安全，
in addition to type safety,
还有具有垃圾收集器的自动内存管理，
you know there's automatic memory management with garbage collector,
所以释放是很简单的，
so freeing is easy,
你不用考虑它，
you don't have to think about it,
垃圾收集器会帮你做所有的工作，
the garbage collector does all the work for you,
它对并发性有好处，
it's good for concurrency,
它有很好的抽象性，
you know it has good abstractions,
比如 Go 它的接口或其他一些类或其他形式的，
you know it's like Go its interfaces or some other classes or some other form of,
这会鼓励你编写模块化代码。
you know forces you or encourage you to actually write modular code.
不好的一面，你可能会想，
The downsides and you might be wondering like,
如果高级语言有这么多好处，
oh if there's so many upsides to high-level languages,
为什么不，
you know why not,
为什么 xv6 不是用 Java Go Python 或其他什么来写，
you know why is xv6 not written in you know Java Go Python or whatever,
原因是， Linux ，
and the reason is you know the or Linux,
原因是它的性能很差，
you know the reason is there's poor performance,
高级语言是要付出代价的，
you know there's a cost to actually a high-level language,
有时这被称为高级语言税。
sometimes this is referred to as the high-level language tax.
这些是，如果你做一个数组界限，数组索引，
And you know these are basically you know if you do an array bounds, array index,
你必须检查边界，
you know you have to check the bounds,
你必须检查空指针，
you know you have to check nil-pointers,
它们有更昂贵的转换，
and they have more expensive cast,
垃圾收集也不是免费的，
and you know garbage collection itself is also not free,
要花几个周期来追踪，
you know there's gonna be some cycles spent tracking down
哪些对象是空闲的，哪些是分配的，这是也是损失。
which objects are free, which are allocated, then you know that's a cost.
所以这是从性能方面，
So that's you know from the performance side
很多论文都集中在这一点。
and a lot of the paper focuses on this.
然后原则上，我的意思是，
And then in principle you know often I mean
它被认为是与 Linux 内核编程的不兼容，
it's perceived as a sort of incompatibility with Linux kernel programming,
没有直接的内存访问，
you know no direct memory access,
因为原则可能知道违反了类型安全，
you know, because the principal could know a violate type safety,
没有手写汇编语言，
no hand-written assembly
你需要在内核中使用一些手写汇编语言，
and you need some hand-written assembly in the kernel,
在两个线程之间的上下文切换，
whereas the context switch between two threads
或者在机器启动时顺利开始，
or to get off the ground when the machine boots,
通常情况下，
in you know often,
语言可能有一个特定的并发或并行的计划，
you know the language may have a particular plan for concurrency or parallelism
可能与内核需要的并发并行不一致，
that might not line up with the plan that the kernel needs work concurrency parallelism,
我们已经看到，比如在调度课程中，
we've seen for example and a scheduling lecture,
一个线程将锁传递给另一个线程，
you know one thread passes a lock to another thread,
有几种并发管理的模式，
where you know there's a couple you know there's patterns of concurrency management
这些都是不普通或普通的程序，
that are sort of unusual and usual programs,
但它们确实出现在内核中。
but they do show up in, in kernels.
所以，这个论文的目标是，
So, so the goal basically of this you know paper was
衡量高级语言的权衡，
to sort of measure the high-level language trade-offs,
探索使用高级语言代替 C 语言的总体效果，
explore the total effects of using high-level language instead of C,
不仅是在安全编程能力方面，
you know both in terms of a safety program ability,
而且在性能成本方面。
but also for performance cost.
当然，如果你想做这个实验，
And of course if you'd like to do this, this kind of experiment,
你需要做那种生产级的内核，
you know you need to do that sort of a production grade kernel,
你不能在 xv6 上做到这一点，
you can't do that on xv6,
因为它太慢了，你可能什么都学不到，
because it's so slow that basically you probably won't learn anything,
这是一个用 C 语言写得很慢的程序，
you know it's a program that was written slow in C,
你用 Go 也写得很慢，
you're written slow in Go,
这并不能告诉你很多关于 C 对 Go 的问题，
you know doesn't really tell you much about you know the C versus Go question,
它只是说 xv6 很慢。
it just says like well xv6 slow.
所以你想要在一个更高性能的内核，
And so you want to do that in a more high performance you know oriented kernel
或者内核是为高性能而设计的。
or the kernel was designed for high performance.
所以你知道有一件事是令人惊讶的，
And so you're you know one of the things that are surprising,
因为你们中的许多人问到这个，
because like many of you ask this [] ask this
我想这个问题一定会在文献中得到回答，
and I would imagine well this question must be answered in the literature,
事实证明这并不是，
and you know it turns out that actually isn't,
有很多的研究这个问题，
it is there's quite a number of studies that look into the question
关于高级语言在用户程序中的权衡的问题，
of high-level language trade-offs in the context of user programs,
但是内核和用户程序有很大的不同，
and, but you know as you know the kernel is quite a bit different from user programs,
比如仔细的内存管理是非常重要的，
for example memory management, careful memory management is really important,
这种不同类型的并发性可能略有不同，
this different types of concurrency may be slightly different,
所以我们想在内核中做这件事。
so we want to do it in the context of a kernel.
我们没有找到任何论文真正回答这个问题，
And we don't actually really find any sort of papers really answer this question,
你能接近的是，
the closer you could come to is,
有很多内核是用高级语言编写的，
there you know there are many kernels written in high-level language,
这样做已经有很长的历史了，
you know there's a long history of doing that,
甚至可以追溯到早期的机器，
they're dating back even to sort of the early [] machines,
但是很多这些内核的最新版本，
and you know but many of the sort of recent versions of these kernels
并不是根据评估高级语言税问题的想法来做的，
are not really written with the idea of evaluating this high-level language tax question,
而是真正探索新的操作系统设计和新的操作系统架构，
but really to explore new OS designs and new OS architectures,
所以它们没有一个是直接评估，
and so none of them really measured directly,
比如面对面的比较，
you know sort of head to head comparison,
保持结构不变，
and keep the structure the same,
所以你可以真正专注于语言的问题，
so you can really focus on this issue of the language
而不是其他问题。
as opposed to some other issues.
事实上，我们过去读过一些论文。
In fact we used to read you know some of these papers actually in the past.
所以，有一个原因可能是，
So, you know there's one reason may be that,
没有太多的工作回答，
there's not a lot of work that actually answers,
很多论文没有回答这个问题，
a ton of papers not answer this question is,
做这件事是很困难的，
it's actually tricky to do it,
如果你真的想做它，
basically if you really do it right,
想和一个 C 编写的生产级别的内核进行比较，
you know you want to compare with a production grade C kernel,
比如 Linux 或 Windows 之类的东西，
that means something like Linux or something that Windows whatever,
然后你必须构建一个产品级别的内核，
but then you have to build a production grade kernel
当然，对于一个小团队来说，这是很难做到的，
and you know clearly for a small team that is very hard to do,
你知道有很多 Linux 内核开发者，
you know there's lots of lots of Linux kernel developers,
做了很多修改，一周又一周，一天又一天，
make many many changes you know week by week day by day
所以很难做到，
and so it's going to be hard to
做同样的事情，
you know to do the same thing
构建一个同类型的东西，
and build an equivalent you know type of thing,
所以你只能满足于稍微低于。
so you have to settle for something slightly less than.
所以，我们能做的最好的是，
So the best we could do or the best we could come up to do is
构建一个高级语言的内核，
build a high-level build a kernel on the high-level language,
保持大部分重要方面与 Linux 相同，
you know keep most of the important aspects of same as Linux,
优化性能，
optimized performance,
优化性能，直到与 Linux 大致相似，
roughly optimized performance until it's roughly similar to Linux,
即使它可能不是完全相同的特性，
you know even though maybe it's not identically exactly identical features,
但它进入了同样的范围内，
but it gets into the same ballpark
然后评估高级语言的权衡。
and then measured high-level language trade-offs.
当然，这种方法的风险是，
And of course you know the risk you know this approach is that
我们构建的内核实际上与 Linux 略有不同，
you know the kernel that we built you know actually is slightly different than Linux,
它不会和 Linux 完全一样，
you know it's not gonna be exactly like Linux
所以当你得出任何结论时，必须非常小心。
and so you've gotta be very careful when drawing any conclusions.
这是一个原因，
And you know and this is one reason
为什么我们仍然可以得到一个相当清晰的答案，
why you can still get a really crystal clear answer,
这就是这篇论文提出的问题，
that is the question that basically this paper proposes,
但我们希望能获得更深层次的洞察力，
but we can hopefully get a little bit more deeper insight
而不是基本上什么都不说。
than basically saying almost nothing about it.
这能理解吗，到目前为止，有什么问题吗？
Is this makes sense, so far, any questions?
这就是这篇论文的背景，
That's sort of the context of this paper,
以及为什么我们这么做。
and you know why we gone to do it.
好的，如果没有问题，
Okay so, if there's no questions,
我想多谈一点关于方法论的问题。
I'd like to talk a little bit more about the methodology.
所以，基本的设置是，
So, so basically you know the sort of setup is
在左边，有我们的 Biscuit ，
here on the left side, you know we have our is gonna be Biscuit,
我们要，在我们的情况中，
you know, we're gonna, in our particular case,
我们为这篇论文使用 Go 编写的内核，
we wrote for this paper the kernel in Go,
它提供了与 Linux 的系统调用大致相同的子集，
it provides roughly a similar subset of the system calls Linux provides,
你知道它们的方式，
but you know the way to,
它们有相同的参数，
but they have same arguments,
相同的的调用接口。
you know the same calling interfaces.
我们在接口上运行相同的应用程序，
And we run basically the same applications on top of that interface,
其中一个应用程序是网络服务器 Nginx ，
so you know one of the applications and Nginx which is a web server,
所以我们的想法是，
and so the idea is that
我们在 Biscuit 和 Linux 上使用相同的应用程序，
you know we're on the same application both on Biscuit and Linux,
应用程序使用完全相同的参数生成相同的系统调用[跟踪]，
you know the application will generate the same system call trace with exactly the same arguments
Biscuit 和 Linux 执行所有必须的操作，
and both Biscuit and Linux you know perform all the necessary operations
由这些系统调用引起的，
that are invoked by those system calls,
然后我们可以看一下
and then we can sort of look at you know
高级语言内核和 Linux 之间的区别，
the difference is basically between you know the high-level language kernel and Linux,
并讨论一下什么是权衡。
and sort of talk about like you know what are the trade-offs.
所以在方法论之后，
And so after the core of the methodology
因为 Linux 和 Biscuit 不会完全相同，
and again because Linux and Biscuit are not going to be exactly identical,
这里会有一些不同，
you know there's gonna be some differences,
但是我们在这里花了很多时间，
but you know we spend a lot of time in this
尽可能地进行比较，
trying to you know make comparison as far as possible,
尽可能想办法做成它。
wherever possible we could think of making it.
你们中的很多人都会问这个问题，
So a lot of you ask this question
使用哪种高级语言，
which high-level language use,
对于这种工作，
you know for this kind of work
我们选择 Go ，出于几个原因，
and you know we pick Go and for a couple of reasons,
它是一种静态编译语言，
it is a statically compiled language,
所以与 Python 不同，这里没有解释器，
so unlike Python, there's no interpreter,
这是我们喜欢静态编译的原因，
and the reason that we like static compiled,
因为我们可以编译高性能的代码，
because we've basically compiles actually high performance code,
实际上， Go 编译器是相当不错的。
in fact the particular Go compiler is pretty good.
所以它是一种高性能的语言，
So basically you know sort of high performance language,
此外， Go 的设计是为系统编程的，
furthermore, Go design is actually intended for system programming
内核或系统编程，
you know kernels or for system programming,
所以它是一个很好的选择。
so that could be a good match.
举个例子，为什么它是一个好的系统编程语言，
As an example, you know aspect of why it's a good system programming,
它很容易调用汇编或其他外来代码，
it's actually easy to call assembly or other foreign code,
它对并发有很好的支持，非常方便。
it has good support for concurrency, quite flexible.
然后另一个我们想要使用它的原因，
And then another reason that we wanted to use it,
因为它有一个垃圾收集器，
because it has a garbage collector,
关于高级语言需要考虑的一件事，
one of the things that you think about a high-level language,
高级语言的优点之一，
and one of the virtues of a high-level languages
你不需要进行内存管理，
that you don't have to do memory management,
垃圾收集器通常是关键角色，
and garbage collectors typically in a central role in the,
在内存管理中提供关键角色。
yeah, provides a central role in a sort of memory management story.
当我们开始写这篇论文的时候，
By the time we started this paper,
或者我们开始这个项目的时候，
or we started this project,
Rust 不是很流行，
Rust was not very popular
或者 Rust 还不是很稳定和成熟，
or Rust was not very stable and mature at that point,
它可以写一个真正的内核，
and the actually could write a real kernel,
现在回想一下，
in a retrospect now,
如果你再做一次，
you do it again,
你可以使用 Rust 来写，
you know you may write it in Rust,
因为它也是为系统编程设计的，
because it also designs for system programming,
它有一个很小的运行时，可以产生好的代码，
it has a small runtime, produces good code,
尽管有一件事，
although one thing that
可能仍然会让人[本能地]去尝试的是，
actually might still make it very [instinct] to go for Go is that,
Rust 首先假设，
Rust takes the starting assumption
如果你想要高性能系统程序，
that that if you want high performance systems programs,
那么你不能使用垃圾收集器。
then you can't do that with a garbage collector.
事实上， Rust 类型系统以一种非常聪明的方式，
And in fact a Rust type system is set up in a very clever way
和一种非常有趣的方式设置的，
and a very interesting way,
所以垃圾收集器是不必要的。
so that actually the garbage collector is not necessary.
在某些方面，我们对回答这个问题很感兴趣，
And in some ways, we were interested in answering this question,
在高级语言中进行垃圾收集的成本是多少，
what is the cost of garbage collection in a high-level language,
关于内核编程，
you know on kernel programming
它的成本是多少，
and it is really impossible to use or what does that cost,
在某些方面， Rust 绕过了这个问题，
in some ways, you know Rust sidestep that question
使用一种没有垃圾回收的语言，
and just like you know use a language without garbage collection,
你不必须考虑这个成本。
you haven't to think about this particular cost.
关于这个有什么问题吗，
Any questions about this,
关于我们决定使用的编程语言方面。
in terms of the programming language we decided to use.
许多邮件里的问题与这个主题有关。
Lots of email questions related to this topic.
这是一个理论问题，
This is a theoretical question,
可能没有直接的答案，
that maybe doesn't have an immediate answer,
但是如果编写 Linux 内核使用 Rust 而不是 Go ，
but if the Linux kernel were to be written on Rust not Go,
在相同的能力下进行优化，
and like optimized in the same capacity,
它是否能够实现更高的性能？
would it be able to achieve higher performance?
比 Go 的并发吗？
Than, than the Go concurrency?
比 C ，比如 C 编写的 Linux 内核。
Than C, like a Linux C kernel.
我怀疑它会，
I doubt it will be,
好的，很难知道，只是猜测，
okay, hard to know, just speculation, correct,
因为我们做有过这个实验，
because we haven't done this experiment,
在我看来，不会比 C 有更高的性能，
in my senses, you know would be not higher performance than C,
但可能大致相同。
but you know probably roughly the same ballpark.
因为 C 是低级语言，
Because C so low-level,
你可以假设你在 Rust 里所做的，
you can assume whatever you do in Rust,
你也可以用 C 来做。
you could also have done in C.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
好的，谢谢。
Yes, thank you.
好的。
Okay.
好的，我们开始吧，
Okay, so let's move on them,
除非对于这个还有任何其他问题，
unless there are any other further questions about this,
再说一次，请随意打断，
and again feel free to interrupt
这里一节基于讨论的课程，
and you know there's a bit of a discussion based lecture,
它的目的是激发智力和兴趣，
and so it was intended to stimulate intellectual interests,
所以，如果你对这个话题有什么想说的，可以加入进来。
so you jump in if you have anything to think about this topic.
所以在我想问的问题之前，
So actually before you know maybe the question I want to ask,
也许我会在课程结束时回来看，
maybe I'll come back to that at the end of the lecture,
课程快结束的时候。
closer to the end of the lecture.
在一定程度上，我们使用高级语言
Partly you know the whole reason we ought to use high-level languages
来避免某种类型的 bug ，
to avoid sort of class of bugs
你应该问自己一个问题，
and one question you should ask yourself,
你在实验中出现的哪种 bug 是可以避免的，
where bugs you know in the labs that you had that would have been avoided,
如果你使用高级语言。
if you had a high level language.
所以回想一下，
You know, so you know think back,
我相信你能想出一些 bug ，
you know I'm sure you can come up with some bugs,
花了你很多时间和痛苦，
that you cost you a lot of time and a lot of pain,
你可以问自己这些 bug ，
and you could ask yourself those kind of bugs,
如果我们在实验中的 xv6 ，
you know if we if the xv6 where we run into labs
用另一种高级编程语言来完成，
would be done in another high-level programming language,
会让生活变得容易很多，
would have life would be a lot easier,
让你有更多的空闲时间做其他事情。
would you have a lot more spare time to do other things.
所以我们带着这个问题，
So let's keep that question in your head
在课程结束时回到这个问题上来。
and you know hopefully return to that at the end of the lecture.
但是如果你现在有想法，也没问题。
But if you have opinions right away, that's fine too.
好的，让我说一下 Biscuit ，
Okay, so let me talk a little bit about Biscuit,
其中的工作，
and you know sort of works
一些惊讶的事情，
in sort of surprises where the things,
我们在构建 Biscuit 过程中的东西，
that we ran into while building Biscuit things,
我们遇到一些没有预料到的东西。
that we anticipated in some things that we actually did not anticipate.
所以用户程序，
So the user programs,
这里有一个传统内核，
there's a classic kernel,
一个与 Linux 或 xv6 相同的宏内核，
a monolithic kernel in the same way to Linux or xv6's,
所以这里有用户空间和内核空间，
and so there's user space and kernel space,
用户空间程序是，
user space programs are
比如你的编译器 GCC ，
you know whatever your compiler GCC
或者在我们的论文中，它是一个网络服务器，
or in our speaking of paper it's mostly a web server,
以及其他一些基准。
and some other benchmarks.
用户程序都是用 C 语言编写的，
And the user programs are actually all written in C,
尽管它可以是任何语言编写的，
although it could be principal in any language,
因为它们只是一个基准，
you know since they're just a benchmark,
我们采用 C 语言版本，
we took C versions,
并且多数程序都是多线程的，
and most of the programs are multi-thread,
所以，与 xv6 中每个用户程序只有一个线程不同，
so unlike in xv6 where basically there's one thread per user program,
在 Biscuit 中，支持多个用户线程。
in Biscuit, actually support multiple user level threads.
对于每个用户线程，
And basically for every user level thread,
在内核中都有相应的内核线程，
there's corresponding kernel thread in kernel,
这些内核线程是由 Go 实现的，
and this kernel threads are actually implemented by Go itself
Go 调用 Go 例程，
and Go calls these Go routines,
你可以把 Go 例程看作普通线程，
you can think about Go routines just as ordinary threads
与 xv6 相同的方式，内核具有线程，
in the same way that xv6 has and the kernel has threads,
Go 协程是类似的，
the Go routines are similar,
主要的区别是，
the main difference it correctly is that,
在 xv6 中，线程是由内核实现的，
in xv6 you know the threads are implemented by the kernel itself,
在这种情况下，是由 Go 运行时提供的，
and in this case you know Go runtime basically provides,
Go 运行时调度它们，
the Go runtime schedules them,
Go 运行时支持睡眠唤醒或条件变量，
Go runtime has support for things like sleep wakeup or condition variables,
有不同的睡眠唤醒，
there's lots of different sleep wakeup,
但有一些条件变量同步机制，
but there's some condition variable synchronization mechanism,
还有很多原语，
and there's a whole bunch of other you know things primitive,
Go 运行时 Go 语言本身提供，
and Go runtime just provided by the Go language itself,
不是由 Biscuit 本身实现的，
and you have not been implemented by Biscuit itself,
我们只是从 Go 运行时获得它们。
we just get them from the Go runtime.
GO 运行时本身直接在裸硬件上运行。
The Go runtime itself runs directly on the bare hardware.
我会在课程中更多地谈到这一点，
And, I'll talk a little bit about that more in the lecture,
但你可以认为这是机器启动，
but like so you think about this is the machine boots,
第一件事就是启动到 Go 运行时，
you know the first thing it actually boots to Go runtime,
这带来了很多复杂情况，
does it cause a lot of complications,
因为通常 Go 运行时作为用户程序运行在用户空间，
because Go runtime that normally runs in user space as user level program
假设有一个内核，
and assumes that the kernel there's a kernel there,
我们可以请求一些服务，
we can ask some services,
比如，需要为其堆分配内存。
for example, needs to allocate memory to, for its heap.
所以这里有一些，
And so there's a little bit of, all talk a little bit about,
有一些垫片代码，
that there's a little bit of shim code,
Biscuit 用来欺骗 Go 进行时，
the Biscuit has to basically trick you know Go runtime
使其相信它运行在操作系统之上，
into believing that it runs on top of the operating system,
即使它是在裸硬件上运行，
even though it's running on bare hardware,
获得启动。
and basically get the boot.
然后内核本身跟 xv6 非常相似，
And then the kernel itself, you know it's very similar, you think xv6,
想象有一种模型，
think there's a model,
不过它更复杂，性能更高，
except it's a little bit more elaborate and more high performance,
它有虚拟内存系统，
it has some virtual memory system,
比如，你这周要做的 mmap 实验，
you know that for example implements mmap lab you're doing this week,
它有一个文件系统，
it has a file system,
有更高性能的文件系统，
like there's more high performance file system,
它有一些驱动，
it has a couple of drivers,
它有磁盘驱动，
you know it has a disk drive
它有网络驱动，有网络堆栈，
and it has a network driver, it has a network stack,
所以它会更完整，
so it will be more complete,
你可以看到，它有大概 58 个系统调用，
and when you can see that is, it has like 58 system calls,
我记不清 xv6 有多少了，
you know like I can't remember how much xv6 has,
但应该是 18 或 19 个左右。
but [startling] the order of 18 19 or something like that.
启动代码的总数是 28000 个，
And the total number of launch code is 28000,
xv6 我想是在 10000 以下，
you know xv6 is like not in, I think below 10000,
所以这里有更多功能。
so you know there's more features.
关于这个高级别的概述，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about sort of this high-level overview?
哦，抱歉，我想问一下接口的事，
Oh, sorry I wanted to ask about the the interface,
所以接口像 xv6 一样，是吗，
so the interface is just like xv6, right,
进程必须把一些东西放在某些寄存器上，
so the processes they have to put something in some register
然后它们调用 ecall ，或者不管它是什么。
and then they call the ecall or whatever it is.
是的，我会再多说一点，
Yeah, yeah I'll talk a little bit more about this,
但它是完全一样的，没有什么不同。
but it's exactly the same, there's no difference.
好的，我明白了，谢谢。
Okay I see, thank you.
一些功能已经提过了，
So some of the features you know already mentioned them a little bit,
或许多核值得讨论一下，
maybe worth talking about its multicore,
Go 对并发的良好支持，
Go with good support for concurrency
Biscuit 的多核，
and so you know Biscuit's multicore,
以同样方式， xv6 对多核的支持有限，
in the same way that xv6 sort of has limited support for multi-core,
在这里，我们有
in this, we have
比 xv6 有更细粒度的同步或协调。
a little bit more fine-grained synchronization or coordination than actually in xv6.
它有用户级线程，
It has threads you know user level threads,
由内核线程[提供]，
[backed] up by kernel threads,
这是 xv6 没有的，
which xv6 doesn't have,
有日志文件系统，具有更高的性能，
there's journal file system much higher performance,
你会在 ext3 论文中看到，
like think you know you'll called the ext3 paper,
就像 ext3 文件系统。
sort of like you know the ext3 generally file system.
它有，相当合理，复杂的存储系统，
It has, you know quite reasonable, sophisticated memory system,
使用 VMA ，
you know using VMAs,
它可以支持 mmap 之类的东西。
and you know it could support mmap and all that stuff.
它有一个完整的 TCP/IP 协议栈，
It has a complete TCP/IP stack,
可以通过互联网与其他网络服务器进行通信，
you know good enough to actually talk to other network servers across the Internet
它有两个高性能的驱动器，
and it has two drivers with high performance drivers,
比如一个万兆网卡，
so like a ten gigabit NIC,
在接下来的实验里，
in the next lab,
你可以实现一个非常简单的网卡的驱动，
you can actually implement a little driver for a very very simple NIC,
这是一个更高性能和更复杂的驱动程序。
this is a much more high performance and sophisticated driver.
在一个相当复杂的驱动程序中，
And in a pretty sophisticated this driver,
比 VIRTIO_DISK 驱动程序更复杂，
you know more sophisticated than the VIRTIO_disk driver,
你可能在实验里见过的。
that you've sort of seen or you might have looked at in the labs.
那么，就我前面提到的一个用户程序，
So in terms of a user programs as I mentioned before,
每个用户程序运行自己的页表，
every user program runs its own page table,
用户内核内存由硬件区分，
user kernel memory isolated by hardware,
使用一个内核位，
so you use a kernel bit basically,
并且每个用户线程都有对应的内核线程，
and every user thread has a corresponding kernel thread,
比如，当用户线程进行系统调用时，
so for example when a user thread makes a system call,
它将继续在相应的内核线程上运行，
it will continue running on the corresponding kernel thread,
如果系统调用阻塞，
and if the system call blocks,
那么另一个在相同地址空间的用户线程，
then another user thread in the same address space
用户地址空间可能会由内核调度。
and the user address space might actually be scheduled by the kernel.
如前所述，
And as mentioned early,
内核线程是由 Go 运行时提供的，
kernel threads are provided by the Go runtime
所以它们只是 Go 协程。
and so they just Go routines.
所以，如果你编写过，
So you're write ever user level,
如果你使用 Go 编写过用户程序，
if you ever written a user level application in Go
并使用 Go 调用来创建线程，
and using Go and used to Go call to create a thread,
那些 Go 协程就是
you know that those those Go routines are the ones
Biscuit 内核使用的。
that were actually being used by the Biscuit kernel.
说到系统调用，
So talking about system calls,
这个问题是刚刚被问到的，
you know this question is just asked,
它的工作原理与 xv6 中大致相同，
so it works exactly as roughly you know as in xv6,
用户线程将参数放入寄存器中，
you know the user thread put arguments in registers
使用一个小的库，
using a little library,
它提供了系统调用接口，
you know that provides system call interface,
然后用户线程执行 SYSENTER 调用，
then the user threads executed SYSENTER call,
Biscuit 在 x86 处理器上运行，
you know this Biscuit runs on an x86 processor
而不是在 RISC-V 处理器上，
not on the RISC-V processor,
x86 系统内核中的汇编指令
so the assembly instructions for actually Intel system kernel
与 RISC-V 上的略有不同，
are slightly different than on the RISC-V on the RISC-V,
但是与 RISC-V 类似，
but you know roughly similar similar to RISC-V,
然后控制权传递给内核线程，
and then control passes to the kernel thread,
运行那个用户线程的（内核线程），
that was running that user thread,
然后内核线程执行系统调用，
and then the kernel thread executes a system call,
然后使用 SYSEXIT 返回。
and then returns use SYSEXIT.
大致相同的框架，
So roughly similar frame,
它建立一个 trapframe 和其他东西，
you know it's a trapframe that's being built and all that kind of stuff.
好吗？
Okay.
到目前为止，有什么问题吗，
Any questions so far,
在我深入讨论更多之前，
before I dive into sort of a more sort of,
意料之外和意料之内的东西，
things that were unexpected or expected,
但我们会有更多不同的挑战，
but we're a little bit more challenging than were different,
我想与 xv6 比起来。
that I think it would go in the xv6.
我有个问题，
I have a question,
我想，我认为,
I guess, I think,
Go 希望你更多地使用管道而不是互斥锁，
Go wants you to use channels more than mutex locks,
我想，会不会是，
I guess, so would you like, would there be like,
xv6 中某些东西的设计，
what the design of somethings in xv6 be like,
可以使用管道，而不是持有锁。
could use as channels instead of holding a lock for something.
是的，这是一个很好的问题，
Yeah, there's a great a great question,
我会在再次回到这个问题上，
so we I'll come back to it a little bit again,
再往下看，
further down
我们有几张幻灯片，
and we have some slides
关于我们在 Biscuit 中使用了 Go 的哪些特性，
about what features of Go did we use in Biscuit,
但是，我们没有使用很多的管道，
but you know the the [] we didn't have any of using channels that much,
我们主要使用锁和条件变量。
we mostly use locks and condition variables.
所以，跟 xv6 的方法很像，
So in some sense closer to like a way xv6 looks,
而不是使用管道的，
than actually a one you would do then you would do with channels,
我们进行了文件系统设计的实验，
we did experiment actually with designs of the file system
对它使用更多的管道，
that were much more channel heavy,
结果不是很好，
and it didn't work out great,
并且我们得到差的性能，
and we got bad performance,
所以，我们又换回了一种更简单的同步方式，
so yeah we switched back to sort of more a sort of simple style of synchronization
xv6 或 Linux 使用的那样。
xv6 does or Linux uses.
好的，这里有几个难题或挑战，
Okay, so you know a couple sort of a little puzzles or implementation challenges
在我们实现的过程中，
as we went through,
第一，我们必须让运行时在裸机上运行，
one, we gotta get to runtime to work on the bare-metal
这需要，你想要，
and you know that required you know wanted to
对运行时进行零修改，尽可能少地修改，
make of course like zero modifications to the runtime where as little as possible,
让 Go 有新版本的运行时，
so that you know Go come out with a new version of the runtime,
我们可以直接用它。
we could just use it.
事实上，多年来，
In fact, you know through the years,
我们在做这件事，代码也在做这件事，
you know that we worked on this, where the code worked on this,
我们升级了运行库很多次。
we upgraded the runtime many you know number of times.
这是一件好事，
And that was turned out to be a good thing,
事实证明，
and it turned out,
它们并不是很难在裸机上工作。
they were not to be too difficult to actually to get to work on the bare-metal.
Go 是精心设计的，
You know Go in general is designed pretty carefully
对操作系统是不可知的，
to sort of be mostly OS agnostic,
因为它们希望能够运行在多个操作系统上，
because they want to be able to run into many operating system,
所以，它不依赖于大量的操作系统功能。
so it doesn't rely on a ton of OS features.
我们基本上模拟了需要的功能，
And we're basically emulated the features that actually needed,
大多数这些功能，
and mostly those are the features,
使 Go 运行时可以开始运行，
that actually just get off the Go runtime to get started
一旦启动，它就会继续运行。
and once it started, it runs just happily.
我们有一些 Go 协程运行不同应用程序的范围，
We have sort of range that Go routine run different applications,
通常在 Go 程序中，一个单一的应用程序，
normally in Go program correct, you know one single application,
这里，我们使用 Go 协程，
and here now we're using Go routine thread
在不同的用户应用程序之间。
around different user, different user applications.
但是用户应用程序必须与不同的页表一起运行。
And but the user applications have to run with different page tables.
这里的[]是，
And the little you know [] here is that
我们或 Biscuit 不能控制调度器，
you know the we don't control or Biscuit doesn't control the scheduler,
因为我们使用的是未修改的 Go 运行时，
because we're using the Go runtime unmodified,
所以我们使用的是 Go 运行时调度器，
so we're using the Go runtime scheduler,
所以在这个调度器中，我们不能切换页表。
and so in the scheduler, we can't switch page tables.
在 Biscuit 中所做的与 xv6 很像，
So what xv6 in basically what Biscuit does is very similar to xv6,
它切换页表，
it actually switches page tables,
当它从内核空间切换到用户空间，或者相反。
when it changes from kernel to user space or the other way around.
所以当进入和退出内核时，切换页表。
So when entry and exit of the kernel, switch page tables.
这意味着像在 xv6 中，
And that means like in xv6
当你需要复制数据，
and then when you need to copy data
从用户空间到内核空间或相反时，
from user space to kernel space or the other way around,
你必须使用 copyin 和 copyout 函数，
you have to do that sort of using those copyin and copyout functions,
我们在 xv6 中已有的，
that we also have in xv6,
你需要做页表扫描软件。
basically you do the page table walking software.
另一个挑战是设备中断，
Another issue of challenge where little challenge was device interrupts,
Go 运行时通常在用户模式下运行，
and Go runtime normally runs in user mode,
它不会收到来自硬件的中断，
you know it doesn't really get interrupts from the hardware,
但是我们在裸机上使用它，
but we're using it on the bare-metal
所以我们会得到中断，
and so we're going to get interrupts,
时钟中断，网络驱动中断，
time clock interrupts, interrupt from the network driver,
磁盘驱动中断，比如 UART 。
interrupt from the disk driver etc, you know from the UART.
所以我们需要解决这个问题，
And so we need to deal with that
而且在 Go 中也没有这个概念，
and and there's also no notion in Go
在持有锁的同时关闭中断，
you know for switching off interrupts while holding a lock,
因为它只显示用户应用程序，
because just show up user applications,
所以，我们需要对如何写入设备中断很小心，
and so we have a little bit careful how to actually write a device interrupt
我们的做法是，
and basically the way we did it is,
我们在设备中断时几乎什么都不做，
we do almost nothing in the device interrupt,
我们不使用任何锁，
we don't take any locks out,
我们不分配任何内存，
basically we don't allocate any memory,
我们唯一做的是，
the only thing we do is
把标志送到某个没有被中断的地方，
basically sending a flag somewhere that wasn't interrupted
然后唤醒一个有效的 Go 协程来处理中断。
and then wake up a really functional Go routine to actually deal with the interrupt.
而那个 Go 协程，当然你可以使用它的所有 Go 的功能。
And that Go routine, of course you can use all the Go features that it wants.
因为它在中断处理程序的上下文中运行，
Because it does run in the context of an interrupt handler,
只是在正常的 Go 协程中运行。
just it runs in the context of normal normal Go routine.
还有一件令人惊讶的事，
Then one thing that surprises, it was a bit of surprise,
前三件事是完全预料到的，
you know the first three things were completely anticipated,
当构建 Biscuit 时，我们必须要处理的，
that we have to deal with when a building Biscuit,
最让我们惊讶的一件事，
the hardest one that actually had suprised us,
我们学到了很多，
and we learned a lot about,
就是堆耗尽的难题。
it was this puzzle of heap exhaustion.
所以，我将主要讨论堆耗尽的问题，
So I'm going to talk mostly for a little while about heap exhaustion
它是什么，它是怎么来的，
and you know what it is, you know how it comes about
以及我们是如何解决它的，
and how we solved it,
但是在深入讨论这个问题之前，
but maybe before diving into that,
到目前为止，有什么问题吗？
any any questions so far?
好的，都清楚了。
So, [] clear.
好的，那么让我们来讨论一下堆耗尽的问题，
Okay, so let's talk a little bit about heap exhaustion,
我不打算全面深入地讨论论文中的内容，
I'm not going to go with full depth was in the paper,
但至少让你对问题有所了解。
but at least gives you a flavor of what the problem is.
所以，在堆耗尽的情况下，
So in the heap exhaustion,
让我们再次假设这里的蓝框是内核，
you know let's say the blue box here is the kernel again,
内核有一个堆，
and you know the kernel has a heap,
是从动态内存中分配的，
from which delegates dynamically memory,
在 xv6 中，我们没有这样的堆，
in xv6, we don't have such a heap,
因为我们在内核中没有内存分配器，
because we don't have a memory allocator in the kernel,
所有东西都是静态分配的，
everything statically allocated,
但是任何其他内核中，我们都会有一个堆，
but any other kernel we'll have a heap,
你可以调用内核中的 malloc 和 free 。
so you can call malloc, you know and free in the kernel.
这些东西实际上是在堆中分配的，
And you know the things that actually get allocated on the heap,
比如，套接字对象，文件描述符对象或进程对象，
for example you know socket objects or file descriptor objects or process objects,
proc 结构体， fd 结构体，
struct proc, you know struct fd,
所有我们在 xv6 中静态分配的结构体，
all the structures that we basically statically allocated in xv6,
一般的内核，它们会动态分配它们，
normal kernels, they dynamically allocate them,
所以，当你打开新的文件描述符时，
so when you open the new file descriptor,
堆中将分配一个文件描述符对象。
there will be a file descriptor object allocated in the heap.
所以，问题是，
And so, then the problem is,
如果你运行多个应用程序，
if you're running many applications,
它们可能会打开很多文件描述符，很多套接字，
you know they might open many file descriptors, may have many sockets,
它们开始缓慢地填满堆，
and they sort of start filling the heap basically slowly,
所以问题是，
and so the issue is that,
在某个时刻，比如堆满了，
at some points, like the heap full,
没有空间用于分配新对象，
there's no space anymore for allocating a new object
或者当应用程序请求打开新的文件描述符时，
or when an application asks for example opens a new file descriptor
有新的进程，新的 fork ，
and there's like you know new process, like there's new fork,
内核想要分配一个 proc 结构体，
and the kernel wants to allocate a struct proc
而堆已经没有空间了。
and heap used like there's no space anymore.
然后你怎么做，
And what did you do that,
你做什么，
you know what is you know,
你怎么处理这个特殊的情况，
how do you deal with that particular case,
这通常，
and this is typically,
可能在通常情况下，不会经常出现，
you know this is maybe in common cases does not show up that often,
但是如果你重度使用机器，
but like if you're pushing machine hard,
你有几个重度的使用者进程运行用户级进程，
you have a couple heavy consumer processes running user level processes,
你可能会遇到这种情况，
you might end in this situation,
所有可用内存都在使用，
where basically in all the available memory is in use
你的堆已经满了。
and your heap is just full.
而且没有进程调用 free ，
And no processes calling free yet,
因为它们都在运行，
you know because they're all running
并试图为它们的工作分配更多的资源。
and trying to allocate more resources for their for their particular jobs.
所以，所有内核都会面临这个问题，
So all kind of kernel face this problem,
不论是 C 内核或 Biscuit 或其他任何东西，
when it like C kernel or Biscuit or anything
任何内核都必须解决这个问题。
and any kernel must solve this particular problem.
它们之所以出现在我们面前，
The reason they they sort of showed up for us
作为 Biscuit 中的一个严重问题，
as a serious issue in Biscuit
是因为在许多内核中，
was because in many kernels the,
你可以在 malloc 上返回错误，
you can return an error on malloc,
xv6 偶尔会这么做，
in fact the xv6 does that, right, once in a while,
但是在 Go 运行时中，
but you know in Go runtime,
当你调用 new 来分配 Go 对象时，
when you call new to allocate a Go object,
没有错误条件， new 就成功了，
there's no error condition, new succeeds,
所以没有办法让它失败。
and so there's no way to fail it.
所以让我们讨论一下解决这个问题的可能的方法，
So let's talk a little bit about possible ways to solve this problem,
我们偶尔会在 xv6 上看到它，
the, you know we've seen it actually xv6 once in a while,
如果你还记得 bcache ，
like if you remember the bcache,
如果 xv6 找不到新的块，
if xv6 can't find a new block you know to,
一个空闲的块来保存磁盘块，
a free block to use for storage a disk block in,
有时只是抛出 panic 。
actually sometimes just panics.
这显然是一个完全不期望的解决方案，
You know this clearly is a completely undesirable solution
也不是一个真正的解决方案，
and it's not a real solution,
所以我们称为 strawman 解决方案。
so why we call it a strawman solution.
另一种 strawman 解决方案是，
The other strawman solution is to,
当你调用，比如分配一块新的内存时，
when you call, let's say you allocate a new piece of memory,
你调用 alloc new 来分配它，
you know you go to call alloc, new to actually allocate it,
你可以等待内存分配器，
you could actually you know wait for memory allocator,
它是一个提议，
it going to be one proposal to do,
结果证明不是一个好的提议，
turns out not to be a good proposal,
它不是一个好提议的原因是，你可能会陷入死锁，
and the reason it's not a good proposal is that you may deadlock,
假设下面的场景，
you know, assume the following scenario,
你持有一些，
you're holding some,
比如，内核有一个很大的内核锁，
let's say the kernel has one big kernel lock,
然后调用 malloc ，等待内存分配器，
and you call malloc, you waiting the memory allocator,
那么就没有其他进程可以运行了。
then basically no other process can run.
你的下一个进程中会有死锁，
And you would have a deadlock have in your next process,
它尝试运行，比如释放一些内存，
that would actually try to run for example to free some memory,
不能运行，其实死锁了。
you know couldn't run, actually deadlock.
当然，这是，
Of course, this is,
如果你有一个很大的内核锁，这是一个明显的问题，
if you have a big kernel lock, there's an obvious problem,
但是即使你有一个非常小的，细粒度的锁，
you know, but even if you have a very small, a fine-grained locking,
它很容易运行到这种情况，
it is easy to run in a situation,
等待分配器的进程持有某种锁，
where basically the person or the process that's waiting in the allocator is holding some lock,
而其他进程需要释放内存，
that somebody else needs to actually free the memory,
这会导致你陷入死锁。
and that can get you basically this deadlock situation.
所以我们知道 strawman free 失败了，
And so we're going strawman free is to basically fail,
或者当不再有内存时，
or when you there's no memory anymore,
alloc 返回没有指针，检查没有指针，
alloc returns like no pointer, you check with no pointer,
你不能使用[]来失败。
it's no point you fail use a [].
但是[]并没有那么简单，
But [] is actually not that straightforward,
进程可能已经分配了内存，
you know the process might actually have allocated memory already,
你需要扔掉它，
you need to get rid of that,
你可能已经执行了部分磁盘操作，
you may have done some partial disk operations,
比如，如果你执行多个步骤，
like for example if you do a multi steps,
部分操作可能完成了部分，但不是全部，
you know partial operation maybe have done some of it, but not all of it,
你必须跳出困境。
you have to bail out of that.
所以，要做对是非常困难的。
And so, it turns out to actually get very very hard to get right.
有趣的是，当你深入研究这件事时，
In sort of interesting, you know when digging into this
考虑如何解决这个问题，
and trying to think about how to solve this problem,
Linux 使用了这两种解决方案。
Linux uses both of these solutions.
这两种都有麻烦或问题，
And you know both actually have trouble or problems,
事实上，内核开发人员很难弄清楚这些，
and indeed kernel developers actually have difficulty to actually get this all straight,
如果你对这个很感兴趣，
if you're very interested in this
并且想看一些有趣的讨论，
and you want to see some interesting discussion about this,
在谷歌上搜索 too small to fail，
google for "too small to fail"
有一篇文章谈到了其中的一些复杂情况，
and there's a little article that talks about some of these complications,
释放内存或等待分配器，
you know free memory or waiting in the allocator,
以及可能导致的问题。
and the problem that can cause.
现在，对我们来说，
Now it turns out, for us,
strawman 2 就是解决方案，
you know so strawman 2 be the solution,
你可以想象到，
that you could imagine doing,
但是对于我们来说，
but then for us,
就像前面提到的，这是不可能的，
just as mentioned earlier, this was not possible,
因为 new 不能返回，不能失败，
because new just cannot return, cannot fail,
它总是成功的，
it just always succeeds,
所以在某种程度上，这种情况不会发生。
so we've got a range in some way that this cannot happen.
另外，这两种解决方案都不是特别理想，
Plus neither of these two solutions actually particular ideal,
所以我们要想出一些更好的东西。
so we wanted to come up with something that was potentially better.
到目前为止，关于堆耗尽的设置，有什么问题吗，
Any questions so far, about the setup around heap exhaustion,
在我谈论 Biscuit 是怎么做的之前。
before I talk about like how the way Biscuit does it.
这个问题能理解吗？
This problem makes sense?
我理解为“是的”，然后继续，
I'll interpret the signings as yes, then keep going,
但可以随时可以打断。
but figure to interrupt anytime.
好的，那么 Biscuit 的解决方案是什么，
Okay, so what is the Biscuit solution,
从高层级来看， Biscuit 的解决方案几乎是直截了当的，
yeah, as a high level of the Biscuit solution is like almost straight forward,
它所做的是，
what basically does,
当你执行系统调用比如 read 或 fork ，
like when you execute a system call like say you read or fork,
在进入 fork 系统调用之前，
before jumping actually into the fork system call,
在 fork 系统调用的开始的地方，
right at the beginning of the fork system call,
比如 xv6 中的系统调用调度器，
if you know like in a system call scheduler in xv6,
然后，它做的第一件事就是调用 reserve ，
then first thing it does actually calls reserve,
它保留了足够的内存，
and it basically reserves enough memory,
以便能够执行系统调用。
to be able to execute the system call.
所以有足够的空闲内存，
So there's a free memory enough
无论系统调用需要的内存是什么，
that actually whatever on memory that actually the system call needs,
保留会足够大，也会成功。
the reservation will be big enough that actually and will succeed.
所以，一旦系统调用开始，
So, so once the system call goes off
并且成功地保留了内存，
and actually successful in reserving memory,
它会一直运行，
it will actually run all the way through
我们不会再遇到这个问题，
and we were never with the problems,
这里没有足够的内存或堆耗尽。
that there won't be enough memory or heap exhaustion.
如果没有足够的内存，
And if there's not enough memory,
在你想要预留的时候，
at the point you want to do the reservation,
那就在这里等待，
then basically just wait here,
但是在系统调用开始时，
but at the beginning of the system call,
系统调用不持有任何锁，
the system call doesn't hold any locks,
没有持有任何资源，
doesn't hold any resources yet,
所以它是非常好的，
so it actually is perfectly fine,
在这里等待，没有死锁的风险。
you know wait there, no risk of deadlock.
当它在等待的时候，
And while it's waiting,
它当然可以做，它可以调用，
you know it can of course be doing, it can call,
内核可以驱逐缓存，
kernel can actually evict cache,
尝试减少，释放堆空间，
you know try to reduce the, basically make free up heap space,
也许像你看到的，
maybe as you seen,
也许会杀死一个进程，强制释放内存。
maybe kill a process that to force you know memory actually be freed.
然后一旦内存可用，
And then once you know memory is available
内核决定，可以满足预订，
and the kernel decides well you know I can meet a reservation,
然后它会让系统调用开始并运行，
then it will let the system call basically goes off and runs,
然后执行它需要做的任何事情，
and basically executes whatever it needs to be done
然后在最后，当系统调用完成时，
and then at the very end, when the system call goes down,
它说，好的，我完成了，
it's like, okay, I'm done,
所有保留的内存都回到池中，
and all the memory that was reserve basically comes back to the pool,
可用于后续的系统调用。
available for subsequent system calls.
这个解决方案有几个很好的特性，
And there's a couple of nice properties about this particular solutions,
内核本身不需要检查，
there's no checks necessary in the kernel itself,
你永远不需要检查内存分配是否会失败，
like you never have to check whether memory memory allocation can fail,
这在我们的情况下很好，
which is particularly in our case good,
因为 Go 是不会失败的。
because you know Go, it can't fail.
这里不需要错误处理代码，
There's no error handling code and necessary at all,
而且没有死锁的风险，
and there's no risk for deadlock,
因为你在一开始就避免了，
because you're avoiding in the very beginning without,
没有持有锁。
when you actually hold no locks.
当然，有很多很棒的，
Of course, you know there's all wonderful well,
唯一的问题是一个挑战，
the only thing is like how there's a challenge,
你怎么做预留，
of course, how you do the reservation,
你怎么计算，
how do you compute,
系统调用需要多少内存来执行它。
you know, how much memory a system call might need to to execute it.
所以现在我们有了一个难题。
And so now we have a puzzle.
你保留的数量是很重要的，
And you know it's important that the amount you reserve,
你可以做的一件事是，
one, one you could do is
你可以保留一半的内存或类似的东西，
you can reserve half memory or something like that,
对每个系统调用来说都是夸张的内存量，
some ridiculous amount of memory for every system call,
但也这意味着你限制了可以并发执行的系统调用的数量，
but that means you limit the number of system calls you can execute concurrently,
所以你想在某种程度上把工作做得很好，
so you want to sort of do a pretty good job
计算出内存量边界，
and actually computing bound of the amount of memory
系统调用可能需要的（内存量）。
that the system call might need.
所以，我们做这件事的方式，
So, the way, we ended up doing this,
是高级语言帮助我们的，
you know turned out like sort of high-level language help us here,
Go 是很容易在进行静态分析的，
turned out like Go is actually pretty easy to static analyze,
事实上， Go 运行时和 Go 基础架构生态系统
in fact Go runtime and Go infrastructure ecosystems
附带了很多用于分析 Go 代码的软件包。
comes with a whole bunch of packages to analyze Go code.
我们使用这些软件包来计算
And we use those packages basically to compute
系统调用需要的内存量，
the amount of memory that the system call needs,
所以你可以考虑，
so you can think about the,
比如，你有一个 read 系统调用，
let's say you have a read system call, right,
我们可以查看系统调用的调用图，
you know you know we could look at the call graph of the system call,
调用函数 f ，调用函数 g ，调用函数 h ，等等，
you know calls the function f, calls the function g, calls the function h, blah blah blah,
可能会有很多，
might continue a whole bunch,
在系统调用结束时，
and you know at the end of system call,
它再次[绑定]到[堆栈]，
it [binds] to [stack] again,
然后返回到用户空间。
and then goes back to return to user space.
我们能做的就是，
And basically what we can do is
分配，或者计算出最大深度，
like you know allocate you know or figure out what the maximum depth,
关于这张调用图，
you know of this this call graph is,
在任何时间，
at any particular time,
然后对于这个最大深度，
and then basically for that maximum depth,
计算出每个函数需要多少实时内存，
you know compute how much you know live memory each of these functions need,
所以，如果函数调用 new ，分配内存，
so if this function calls new, you know that will allocate memory,
我们知道这里有什么类型的对象，
you know we know what kind of objects there are,
我们使用高级语言，
there's a high level language,
所以我们可以计算出对象的大小，
so we can compute the size of that object is,
我们可以把它们加起来，得到一个数字 s ，
we can just add them up and it gives us some number s,
也就是说，内存总量或最大内存量，
that says like the total amount of memory or the maximum amount of memory,
那个调用图可以在任何时间活动。
that can be live at any particular point of time for that call graph.
原因是，这有点棘手，
And the reason is you know it's slightly tricky,
它不是这么简单的，
it's not as simple as this,
因为，比如函数 h 可能分配了一些内存，
because for example a function h might allocate some memory,
然后传递回 g ，
and then pass back to g,
所以 h 结束了，
and so you know h finishes,
但是 g 得到了 h 分配的内存，
and but you know g actually you know gets the memory that h is allocated,
这称为逃逸，
and this is called escaping,
内存从 h 逃逸到 g ，
the memory escapes from you know from h to g
有一些标准算法做这种逃逸分析，
it turns out, there are standard algorithms were doing sort of this escape analysis
确定哪些变量逃逸到调用方，
to see determine which variables escape to the callers,
在这种情况下，
and in that case,
无论 h 分配的是什么内存，它仍然是活动的，
you know basically whatever memory was allocated by h and that's still alive,
我们必须加上 g 的，
we have to add to whatever g is,
所以我们必须加到 s 中。
so you know we have to be added into s.
关于这个，我有一个简短的问题，
A quick question about this,
所以让我们在一些函数中做更多假设，
so let's assume more in some function,
根据函数预期的不同工作负荷，
depending on different workloads that the function is expected to have,
可能分配了不同的内存量，
there might be different memories memory amounts allocated,
那么是否有内存分配进程的最坏情况？
so what is there like a worst-case, what memory allocation process.
是的，这是一种保守的方案，
Yeah, that's basically it's sort of conservative scheme correct,
我们计算，这个工具计算，
and we we computed, the tool computes,
最坏的函数调用深度。
basically a worst possible depth of function calls.
从最坏的情况来看，
And you know for that the worst-case,
分析系统调用可能需要多少内存，
analysis how much memory that reaches system call might need,
在实践中，系统调用可能需要少得多，
in practice, it might need, there system call might need a lot less,
但是为了保守，
but you know for you know to be conservative,
我们必须为最坏的情况分配打算。
we have to allocate the work we plan for the worst case.
所以我们在这里谈到了几个重要的观点，
And so we've come to a couple of important points here,
因为，一些系统调用比如执行 for 循环，
because you know some system calls for example executive for loop,
这取决于系统调用的参数，
that's depended on argument to the system call, right,
你实际上不能静态地计算出界限是什么，
so you can't actually statically figure out what the bound is,
所以，在很多情况下，我们对代码进行了注释，
and so a number of cases we annotated the code
表示这是循环的最大界限，
to say well this is the maximum bounds of this loop,
你可以假设不会超过这个，
and you can assume it's no more than that,
并用它来实际计算这个数字 s 。
and use that to actually compute this number s.
同样地，如果你有一个递归函数，
Similarly you know, for example if you have a recursive function,
谁知道递归有多深，
you know who knows how deep the recursion is, right,
这也可能依赖于
and that might also be a dependent
动态变量或系统调用的参数。
on a dynamic variable or an argument to a system call.
事实上，我们在某些地方处理 Biscuit ，
In fact, you know we you know we treat Biscuit in some places
避免了递归函数传递，
basically avoid recursive function pass,
所以做这个分析是可能的。
so actually it was possible to do this, you know do this kind of analysis.
所以这种分析不是免费的，
So this kind of analysis not for free,
它不是完全自动的，
it's not completely automatic,
对于这种情况，它需要几天的工作，
it takes a couple days of work you know for this case,
Cody 查看所有这些循环，然后注释。
you know Cody to go through look at all these loops and and annotate.
还有一些 Go 的具体的问题，
You know there are a couple others Go specific issues,
你必须处理，
that you have to deal with
比如切片，它们的大小可能会翻倍，
like slice, you know they might double in size,
如果您在切片中添加一个元素，
if you add an element to slice
那么我们模仿最大容量的切片，
and so we imitate the slices which maximum capacity,
但是为了让这些可行用了很多天的工作，
but I use all sort of doable for a couple days work,
使用这个工具，
and you know using this tool,
你可以得到一个合理的数字，
then you can get a number out there is reasonable good,
在计算最大内存量方面，
in terms of computing on maximum amount of memory
系统调用所需的（最大内存量）。
that a particular system call needs.
所以这就是
And so this is basically how
Biscuit 解决这个问题的方式。
you know we basically Biscuit solves this particular problem.
哦，抱歉，人们还用这个工具做什么，
Oh, sorry, what else are people using this tool for,
比如，他们不是在构建内核，
like they're not, they're not building a kernel,
他们用它做什么？
what are they using it for?
通过静态分析软件包。
Over static analysis package.
是的。
Yeah.
Go 编译器使用它进行各种优化，
Go compiler internally uses it for all kinds of optimizations,
做静态分析，
you know to and do static analysis,
Go 找出最好的方法来编译它。
Go go to figure out the best way to for the best way to compile it.
我明白了，好的，谢谢。
I see, I see, okay, thank you.
所以这是这个软件包最酷的地方之一，
So this is one of the cool things about this package,
编译器可以使用，
you know the compiler happens to use,
我们可以做什么。
you know what we could do.
我们稍后会看到，我们还会使用它的其他几个功能。
We'll see later on, we also use it for a couple other features.
这是非常方便的。
It's very convenient to have.
好的。
Okay.
好的，转到实现，
Okay, turns to the implementation,
与其他内核非常相似，
you know basically basically very similar to other kernels
或者像 xv6 ，除了更高的性能。
or like you know xv6, except more high performance.
我们采用了
You know what we adopted
很多 Linux 内核拥有的优化或智慧，
many of the optimizations or cleverness that the Linux kernel has,
至少在我们试图实现的系统调用上，
at least the system calls that we were trying to implement,
对内核文本使用大页面，以避免 TLB 开销，
you know use large pages for kernel text to avoid TLB cost,
我们有每个 CPU 的网卡传输队列，以避免端口之间的同步，
we have per-CPU NIC transmit queues to avoid synchronization between port,
我们有 RCU ，
we have RCU,
我会更多地讨论目录缓存，
I will talk a little bit more about the directory cache,
它是无锁或无读锁的目录高速缓存，
which is basically lock free or read lock free directory cache,
在学期末，我们将更详细地讨论 RCU ，
at the end of the semester, we'll talk about RCU in more detail,
但是，这里会有一些，
but you know, this could have some too,
一种常见的优化类型，
you know sort of the usual type of optimization,
你需要获得高性能。
that actually you need to get high performance.
我想我们学到的主要教训是，
And the main lesson I think we learned is that
Go 并没有阻碍这些优化的实现，
Go was not standing in the way of implementing these optimizations,
所以这些优化可以用 C 和 Linux 实现，
so these optimizations that were implemented in C and Linux,
我们可以实现相同的优化，
you know we've basically implemented same optimization,
但是在 Go 中实现，
but ever implemented in Go,
所以语言本身不是障碍或问题，
and so the language itself is not a hurdle or a problem,
实际上完全有利于实现这些优化。
in fact completely conducive to actually implementing these optimizations.
要实现这些优化需要做很多工作，
There's a lot of work to implement these optimizations,
但与语言无关。
but irrespective of the language.
好的，这带来了某种评价，
OK, so that brings me sort of to evaluation,
也就是整篇论文的动机，
which is really what the, the motivation of the whole paper was,
试图处理高级语言的好处和成本，
which is like trying to handle on the benefits and the costs of high-level language,
所以，评价可以分成两部分，
so basically, the evaluation sort of split in two parts,
先讨论好处，再讨论成本。
first talking about the benefits and then talking about the costs.
有三个问题，
So, so three questions,
首先，有一个问题，比如没有作弊，
you know first of all, you know there's a question like didn't cheat,
也许我们避开了所有昂贵的高级语言特性，
you know maybe we avoided all the expensive high-level language features,
Go 提供的。
that Go offers.
第二个问题，当然是高级语言有没有简化 Biscuit 代码，
Does the, second question of course does the high-level language simplify the Biscuit code,
并且会阻止一些漏洞，
and would to prevent some of these exploits
那些我在课程前面提到的。
that you know I mentioned early on in the lecture.
首先，关于使用高级语言特性，
So first, respect to use high-level language features,
我们希望看到，
we just wanted to see
我们是否与其他大的 Go 项目类似，
whether we were similar in terms of other big Go projects,
在语言功能方面，
in terms of language features,
所以我们可以说，
so that we could say,
整个内核做了，
like all the kernel seems to be doing roughly
以相似的方式做相同功能，有相同的优点。
the same advantage of the same features in similar ways.
所以我们使用相同的静态分析工具
So we use actually the same static analysis tool or package
从根本上分析 GitHub 上的两个大的 Go 软件，
to basically analyze whole bunch of two big pieces of Go software that on github,
它们有数百万行代码，
you know there are millions lines of code,
一个是 Go 运行时本身和所有它的包，
one is you know Go runtime itself and all its packages
另一个是系统 Moby 。
and the system called Moby.
然后，我们计算高级语言特性出现的次数，
And then we just basically product for number of high-level language features,
每千行用了多少次，
how many times they were used for thousand lines,
这张图显示这些，
so this graph shows that,
x 轴是语言特性。
as usual, on the x-axis are the language features.
allocations 对应于调用 new ，
Basically allocations correspond to calling new
这对应于内存，
and so this corresponds to the memory,
由垃圾收集器动态分配。
that it will be dynamically allocated by the garbage collector.
maps 对应于哈希表，切片或动态数组，
You know maps are like hash tables, slices or dynamic arrays.
这是 channel 同步，
You know, here's the channels synchronization,
正如你所看到的，我们很少使用它，
as you can see, we use it very littlely,
但是 Go 运行时和 Moby 也是如此。
but so does the Go runtime and the Moby.
显然，我们最喜欢的特性，
Clearly the feature that we like most,
它是函数多返回，能够返回多个值。
it was multi function return, being able to return multiple values.
我们使用闭包，
You know we use closures,
我们没有使用 finalizer ，
we didn't use finalizer,
我们使用了一些 defer ，
we use defer a little bit,
我们创造了很多 Go 协程，
you know there's a bunch of Go routines that we do create,
我们使用接口。
we use interfaces.
类型断言，从一种类型转换为另一种类型，
You know type assertions to convert from one type to another,
关于类型断言。
in the type asserts matter.
并且导入很多包，
And importing many packages,
内核本身是由多个软件包构建的，
so kernel selves build out of any packages
而不是一个大的单一程序。
are not like one big single program.
所以，如果你看这个，
So if you look at this,
一些功能 Biscuit 比 Golang 和 Moby 使用得少，
you know some features you know Biscuit could use less than Golang and Moby
有时可能会或多或少失去一些功能，
and sometimes you know this could lose some features more or roughly in the [],
而不是以任何明显不同的方式。
not not in any sort of distinctly different way.
所以，由此得出的主要结论是，
So the main conclusion from this is
使用了 Go 提供的高级功能，
you know basically uses the high-level features actually Go offers,
不会为了获得好的性能而回避它们。
and doesn't sidestep them to basically get good performance.
好的。
Okay.
我有个问题，
I have a question,
你怎么能数得清所有这些，
how did you, how are you able to count all this,
你使用了静态分析工具吗？
did you use the static analysis tool?
是的，基本上用的是静态分析包，
Yeah basically use static package, static analysis package
然后写了一个使用静态分析包的小程序
and then wrote a little program that uses static analysis packages
检查这些程序中的每一条语句，
to go over every statement in these programs
看看是哪种类型的语句。
and look at what kind of type of statement is.
然后，你可以获取参数
And then, you get the argument
查看参数是如何使用的，
to see how the arguments are being used
这给你一种感觉，关于，
and that gives you a sense about how,
允许你对这些功能计数。
allows you to count these features.
好的。
Okay.
好的，接下来的事情有点主观，
Okay, so the next thing is a little subjective,
高级语言简化了 Biscuit 代码吗？
did the high-level language simplified Biscuit code?
是的，我认为它是这样的，
Yeah, I think it generally did,
所以，举一两个例子进行讨论，
and so argued with one or two examples explicitly,
但是你现在有 GC 分配是非常好的，
but you're now having GC allocation is actually very nice,
也许我可以说明这一点。
and maybe I can make the point,
如果你考虑 xv6 ，
if you think of xv6
或者执行 exec ，
or you do an exec,
在执行 exec 时，
on point of exec,
有很多数据结构需要释放，或者返回到内核，
there's a lot of data structures that need to be freed or return to the kernel
以便以后的进程可以使用，
and so that later process can use,
使用垃圾收集器很容易，
using garbage collector is really easy,
垃圾收集器会处理所有的事情，
you know the garbage collector takes care of all of it,
你不需要做太多。
you know you don't really have to do much.
所以，如果你分配，释放一个地址页面，
So if you allocate you know free an address page,
地址空间对应的 VMA
you know the VMA correspond in address space
也会被垃圾收集器自动释放。
will be automatically freed by the garbage collector too.
是的，所以这很简单，
Yeah, so you know just that as simple,
正如我们前面提到的，
as we mentioned earlier,
多个返回值在编程风格方面非常好，
the multi return values were really nice in terms of programming style,
闭包也很好，
closures were nice,
maps 也很好，
maps were great,
你不需要有很多[]，
you know you don't have to many [],
比如在 xv6 中，
places xv6 for example,
以线性方式查找东西，
you know look up something in a linear fashion,
但是如果你有哈希表或映射作为第一类对象或抽象，
but if you have hash tables or maps as a first class object or abstraction,
程序员不用再那么做，
the programmer you know would never do that,
你使用 map ，运行时将负责高效地执行所有操作。
you use map and the runtime will take care of doing everything efficiently.
所以，我认为定性来说，你得到了更简单的代码。
So, in in fact I think qualitatively, it feels you get simpler code.
但是定性的很清楚，
But as clearly qualitatively,
举一个更具体的例子，
you know just give a little bit more of a concrete example,
高级语言，特别是垃圾收集器大放异彩的地方是，
where really, where sort of high-level language, particular garbage collector shines is
当存在大量并发时，
when there's a lot of concurrency between,
当存在并发线程，
when there's concurrency threads
而线程共享特定的数据项。
and threads actually share a particular shared data item.
举个例子，这是一个简单的例子，
And so for example, here's a simple case,
你可以把这个问题归结为，
you know or you can boil down this question to,
假设动态分配对象，比如一个 buf ，
let's say allocate somehow dynamically object like a buffer,
fork 出一个线程，然后执行那个 buf ，
you know fork a thread you know and that process that buffer,
还有另一个线程也处理 buf ，
and there's another thread that also process buffer
并对这个 buf 执行一些操作。
and do something of this buffer.
当两个线程都完成时，
When both threads are done,
buf 需要释放，
you know the buffer needs to be free,
让它们可以用于后续的内核操作。
so they can be used for later later kernel operations.
问题是，谁应该做这件事，谁来负责，
And the question is like who should do this, who's in charge,
用 C 来协调有点困难，
and there's a little bit difficult to coordinate in C,
因为你必须有某种方法来确定
because you have to have some way of deciding that
buf 并未被使用，
actually the buffer is actually not being used,
如果你使用垃圾收集器，
if you use a garbage collector,
没有什么需要决定的，
there's nothing to decide,
两个线程运行，完成对 buf 的操作后，
basically both threads run when the done of the buffer,
没有线程再指向 buf ，
no thread is pointing to that buffer anymore,
垃圾收集器将从线程堆栈开始跟踪，
the garbage collector you know will trace you know starting from the threads stacks
并且永远不会计算 buf 任何线程堆栈，
and will never you know and will not count buffer any of the thread stacks
所以，垃圾收集器会在稍后的某个时刻释放内存。
and therefore the garbage collector free the memory at some point later.
所以，在垃圾收集语言中，
And so in a garbage collector language,
你根本不必考虑这个问题。
you don't have to think about this problem at all.
有一种你可以解决这个问题的方法，在 C 内核中，
So you know one way you could try to solve this problem, in the kernel like C,
所以你可以计算对象的引用计数，
so you maybe put reference counts on the objects,
引用计数当然要用锁来保护，
the reference count, of course have to be protected by locks,
也许是一些原子操作，
perhaps were some atomic operations
然后，当引用的计数达到零时，
and then when the reference count reaches zero,
你可以取消引用它。
then you can dereference it.
事实证明，
And it turns out,
引用计数中的锁实际上比较昂贵，
like you know locks in reference counts are actually slightly expensive,
如果你想要高性能，
if you wanna high performance,
将并发性扩展到内核数，
you know concurrency and scale up to the number of cores
那么可能会成为一个瓶颈，
and then actually can be a bottleneck,
我们之后会看到，
then we'll see that later
几周后，我们看的论文，
in a couple weeks we read a paper,
非常明确地谈到了这一点。
that actually talks about this very explicitly.
所以人们倾向于，
And so people tend to,
想要做高性能，获得良好的并行性，
want to do high performance, get good parallelism,
人们倾向于避免它们。
people tend to avoid them.
事实上，在特定情况下，
And in fact, in particular scenario,
我们试图避免它们，在读取块中，
we try to avoid them is like in read block,
你希望至少在读取中是无锁的，
you would like to make at least reading sort of lock free,
这样你就不用损失了。
so you don't have to pay the cost.
比如，这是我们这样做的一个代码片段，
And so, for example, here's a code fragment, that we do that,
这里我们有一个 get 函数，
here we have a get function,
用于读取队列的头部，
basically you reads the head of a queue
并返回队列头部的任何内容，
and returns the whatever is at the head of the queue,
它是以一种无锁的方式运行的，
does it basically in a lock free manner,
使用 atomic_load 来读取头部，
use atomic_load to actually read the head,
但是它并没有使用锁，
but it doesn't actually take a lock out,
然后，写入使用了锁。
then, the writer does locks out.
所以这是无锁，而写入不是无锁。
So this is like lock free, the writers not lock free.
这是 Linux 内核中非常常见的风格，
And this is a very common style in the Linux kernel,
所以写入者拿到了锁，
and so the writer actually they takes the lock,
无论查找头部的任何东西，
you know whatever looks at the head,
也许是 pop 函数，将头部从队列中弹出，
maybe is the pop function and pops of the head from the queue,
然后，你可以重复使用它，
and then you know in principle you could reuse it,
然后解锁，当你释放头部时。
and then unlocks, when you free the head.
现在再来一次，
Now again in,
这有一点困难，
you see, there's a little bit difficult,
你什么时候真正释放头部，
when do you actually free the head,
因为可能是这种情况，
because it could be the case,
一些其他的并发线程，
that some other concurrent thread that [],
正好在做这个 atomic_store 之前，
you know just before you did this atomic_store,
这个函数过来，
you know this guy actually came through
得到一个指向那个特定对象的指针，
and basically got a pointer to that particular object,
所以一旦你完成了这个 atomic_store ，
so once you're done with this atomic_store,
你不能释放指针，
you can't actually free the pointer,
因为可能有另一个线程有指向它的指针，
because there could be another thread actually has a pointer to it,
如果你在这里释放它，
and if you free it right here,
你可能会有一个 use-after-free bug。
you could actually have a use-after-free bug.
我们会在几节课中看到，
And so, and so you know we'll see in a couple lectures,
有一种非常聪明的解决方案，
there is currently a very clever solution for this
称为读取复制更新或 RCU ，
which is called read copy update or RCU,
它所做的是，
basically what it does is
推迟释放内存，直到知道它是安全的。
defers free of memory until really knows it's safe.
它有一个非常聪明的方案来决定什么时候它是安全的，
And it has a very clever scheme to actually decide how when it's safe,
但是这个方案有各种各样的限制，
but that scheme does come with all kinds of, comes with restrictions
程序员必须遵守一些规则，
and programmers actually have to obey some set of rules,
你必须遵循他们所谓的 RCU 临界区，
that you must follow for sort of RCU critical sections as they're called,
比如，你不能调用，
for example, you can't call just you can't call,
你不能在 RCU 临界区或调度中进入睡眠。
you can't go to sleep in an RCU critical section or schedule.
所以，尽管 Linux 内核使用非常成功，
And so it turns out you know alrough the Linux kernel uses extremely successful,
但是比较容易出错，
you know a bit error prone
需要仔细的程序才能正确。
and requires careful program to get it right.
在垃圾收集器语言的情况下，比如 Go ，
And in the case of the garbage collector language like you know Go,
这不是问题，
this is a non issue,
因为垃圾收集器会确定某个东西何时不再使用，
because the garbage collector will actually determine when actually something is not in use anymore
然后才会释放它。
and then only then free it.
所以对程序员没有限制，
And so there's nothing really you know there's no restrictions on the programmer,
只是由垃圾收集器来处理。
just taken care of by the garbage collector.
所以这是一个例子，
So that's sort of an example of
在某种程度上更定性或更明确，
you know where sort of more may be qualitatively or more explicit,
你可以从垃圾收集语言的优势中看出。
you can see through the advantage of a garbage collected language.
好的，关于 CVE 我已经提到过了，
Okay, terms of the CVEs you know I sort of mentioned this already,
我们检查了所有的 CVE 并进行人工检查，
we went through all the CVEs and inspected them manually,
然后试着决定 Go 是否能解决这个问题。
and then try to decide whether to actually Go can fix the problem.
有 11 个我们不能确定，
There for 11 them we couldn't figure out,
我们看了解决这个问题的补丁，
you know we looked at the fix, the patch that addresses is,
我们不能确定 Go 的结果会是什么，
we couldn't really figure out what the outcome in Go would like
或者我们如何改变，
or how would manifest or how we change,
我们可以看看如何修复它，
we could see how the implement it to fix,
但是不能决定 Go 是否会避免这个问题。
but couldn't decide whether it actually Go would avoided the problem or not.
CVE 中的多个逻辑错误，
A number of logic bugs in the CVEs
很可能 Go 也会出现与 C 一样的的逻辑错误，
and so presumably Go you would make the same logic bugs in C
结果会是一样的。
and you know the outcome would be the same.
但是大约有 40 个内存安全漏洞，
But then there were about 40 memory safety bugs,
释放后使用或双重释放或越界使用，
use-after-free or double-free or out-of-bounds
这八个消失了，
and in eight of these disappear,
因为垃圾收集器负责处理它们，
because the garbage collector takes care of them
像最后几张幻灯片中描述的那样。
as described in the last couple slides.
在 32 个案例中， Go 会引起 panic ，
And in 32 cases, Go would have generated panic,
因为比如 Go 会超出数组界限，
because for example would Go outside of an array bound,
当然， panic 是不好的，内核会崩溃，
and of course panic is not good, you know the kernel crashes,
但这比安全漏洞要好。
but it's probably better than a security exploit.
所以， 40 个案例，高级语言帮助了我们。
And so you know so 40 cases, you know basically the high-level language helped us.
好的，这就是好的方面，
Okay, so that's the qualitatively of the benefits,
所以现在我想谈谈高级语言的性能成本，
so now I want to talk a little bit about the performance cost,
高级语言税。
the high-level language tax.
在做那之前，
Before doing that,
让我问一下是否有其他问题？
let me ask if there's any more questions?
好的，我要讲一下它们，
Okay, I'm going to go through them,
我不确定能不能讲完全部六个，
I'm not sure we'll make it through all six,
因为我们在最后至少预留几分钟，
because we reserve a couple minutes at least at the end,
我们将回到课程的起点，今天的问题。
it's going to come back to the starting point of the lecture, today's question.
所以要设置实验，
So to set up in terms of experiments,
Biscuit 运行在裸硬件上，
you know the Biscuit runs on raw hardware,
所以这些实验是在小的物理机器上运行的，而不是在 QEMU 上，
so these experiments are on little physical machines, not on top of QEMU,
是 4 核， 2.8Ghz 的英特尔处理器，
is a 4 core, 2.8Ghz Intel processor,
16GB 内存，但禁用了超线程。
16 GB RAM, but Hyperthreads disabled.
我们使用三个应用程序，
We use three applications,
一个 Web 服务器，一个键/值存储
a webserver, a key/value store
和一个邮件服务器基准测试。
and a mail-server benchmark.
这些应用程序都给内核很大的压力，
You know of these applications stress the kernel intensively
所以，它们执行系统调用，
and so they run execute system calls
内核必须做大量工作。
and the kernel must do a lot of work.
你可以看到这个，
And you can see that,
因为这些应用程序中的大部分时间都花在内核中。
because most of the time in these applications is spent in the kernel.
所以第一个问题是，
So first question is like,
Linux 或者 Biscuit 是不是，
is Linux [even] or is Biscuit [even] in the []
生产级别的内核或工业级别的内核，
of production quality the kernel or industrial quality kernel,
所以我们所做的是，
and so what we did,
我们通过比较 Biscuit 和 Linux ，
we compare the absolute through Biscuit and Linux,
对于 Linux ，我们使用的是 4.9 Linux ，
for Linux, we used 4.9 Linux,
现在有点过时了，
a little bit out of date now,
因为论文已经有几年的历史了。
because paper is of course are a couple years old again.
当然，当我们使用 Linux 时，必须禁用所有功能，
But of course when Linux we have to disable all kinds of features
Biscuit 不提供的，
that Biscuit [uses] or doesn't provide I mean,
比如页表隔离，轮询，
so like page-table isolation, retpoline,
各种各样的一些功能，
you know all kinds of you know a long list of features
这些功能不是 Biscuit 所提供的，也不是 xv6 所提供的，
that actually Biscuit doesn't provide nor xv6 provides,
我们在 Linux 上禁用了它们，
and we disable them on Linux
以使比较尽可能地公平。
to make the comparison as fair as possible.
当然，有些功能很难禁用，
And of course you know some features are hard to disable,
我们不能禁用，
you know we were not able to disabled,
但我们试着尽可能靠近。
but you know we tried to get as close as possible.
然后我们测量了吞吐量。
And then we measured basically the throughput.
如你所见， Biscuit 几乎总是比较慢，
And as you can see, the Biscuit is almost always slower,
它总是比 Linux 慢，
which always slower than Linux,
CMailbench 会差大约 10% ，
you know CMailbench, you know it's about to get whatever 10%,
在 Nginx 上，再多一点，
on NGINX a little bit more,
Redis 是 10% 或 15% 。
Redis is a little bit of 10,15 percent.
但是你应该粗粒度地比较这些数字，
But you should use these numbers very grain as result, right,
因为，它们不一样，
because, you know they're not identical,
这不是一一对应的比较，
and it's not apples to apples comparison,
但是首先，
but they like to sort of first order
它们至少是大致相同的，
you know they're roughly the same ballpark at least,
它们不是 2 倍、 3 倍、 4 倍或 10 倍的差距，
you know they're not like 2x 3x 4x or 10x off,
所以，也许真正能够做到这一点是值得的，
and so you know maybe it's worthwhile to actually be able to do actually,
从中得出一些结论。
you know to draw some conclusions out of that.
所以我们看一下，
So then we sort of looked at,
我们分析代码，
like you know we look basically profile the code
并尝试对代码所花费的周期分类，
and try to bucket you know the cycles that were spent by the code,
特别是，我们关注的是垃圾收集器中有哪些循环，
particularly we're looking at which cycles were actually in the garbage collector,
哪些周期在 prologue 函数调用中，
which cycles were actually in the prologue function calls,
Go 的 prologue 做了很多工作，
and prologues in Go does a bunch of work,
确保堆栈足够大，
you know to ensure that the stack is large enough,
可以在堆栈中运行，
so you know run of the stack,
写入屏障循环，这是在垃圾收集器模式时，
write barrier cycles, this is actually when in garbage collector mode,
垃圾收集器打开写入障碍，
you know the garbage collector turns on write barriers
用于跟踪不同空间之间的指针。
to basically track pointers between different spaces.
而安全周期，
And the safety cycles,
安全周期是在列表边界检查上花费的周期，
which are safety cycles are the cycles spent on array bound checks
诸如此类的事情，无指针检查。
and things like that, no pointer checks.
所以如果你看这些应用程序，这里的数字，
And so if you look at these applications you know here the numbers,
3% 的执行时间花在了 GC 周期上，
so 3% of the execution time was actually spent in sort of GC cycles,
我们会稍微讨论一下为什么这个很低，
and I'll talk a little bit about why that's low,
但在这种情况下，
but you know in this case,
垃圾收集器在这些应用程序运行时运行，
that the garbage collector running while running these applications,
所以这不是我们测量应用程序的情况，
so it's not the case that we measured the applications,
我们提供了很多内存，
we give so much memory,
只是运行而不需要垃圾收集器，
that you know just run without actually running the garbage collector,
令人惊讶的是， prologue 周期是最高的，
surprisingly actually the prologue cycles turned out to be the highest,
这就是方案的方式，
and this is basically you know the way the scheme,
我们使用这些时间检查内核堆栈，
that we're using that time for checking whether the kernel stack
或线程堆栈，
or the stack of a thread needed to
或 Go 协程是否需要增长，
or Go routine needed to be grown or not,
而这是 Go 设计中的一种[]，
and this is something that actually the Go design that point in a [],
它可能更容易降低，
that it's probably easier to get lower,
写入屏障的时间很短，
very little time actually write barrier is,
有 2-3% 在安全循环中。
you know 2-3% you know in the safety cycles.
所以在某种意义上，这是个好消息，
And so in some sense, you know there's good news,
你不在，（高级语言）税并不是很大，
you are not at, you know tax is not gigantic,
当然，这个数字可能会高得多，
of course this number could be much higher,
因为这完全取决于堆的数量和大小，
because this is completely dependent on how many, how big you know the heap is
或者活跃的对象的数量，
or live the live number of, live objects is,
因为垃圾收集器必须跟踪所有活动对象
because the garbage collector will have to trace all the live objects
以确定哪些对象是不活动的。
to actually determine which objects are not alive.
所以，如果有很多活的对象，
And so if there's a lot of live objects,
垃圾收集器不得不跟踪更多的对象，
you know the garbage collector will have to trace more objects,
所以这与活跃对象的数量完全成线性关系。
and so this completely sort of linear with the number of live objects.
我们也做了一些其他的实验。
So we did some other experiments.
让我稍微缩小一点，
Let me zoom out a little bit,
我们分配了大量的活动数据，
where we basically allocate a ton of live data,
200 万个虚拟节点，
2 million vnodes,
可以将其视为 200 万个 inode ，
think about this as 2 million inodes
并且释放大量的堆内存，
and a free the amount of heap RAM
或者修改垃圾收集器拥有的堆内存的大小，
or change the amount of heap RAM the garbage collector has,
为了释放内存，
you know for free memory,
然后[]，然后测量成本。
and then [] and then measure the cost.
就是这张表，
So this is the table here,
我们有大约 640 兆字节的活跃数据，
we have like 640 megabytes is live data,
使用不同的内存大小运行，
and there's running with different memory sizes,
在一种大小的情况下，有 320 兆字节的数据，
and one sizes case, there are 320 megabytes of data,
所以活跃与空闲的比是 2 ，
so the ratio of live to free is 2,
你可以看到，在这种情况下，
you see that in that case,
Go 很好地模仿了垃圾收集器的开销，
Go does do a great imitation of [] overhead the garbage collector,
因为垃圾收集器需要运行很多次，
because the garbage collector needs to run a lot,
因为它没有太多堆内存。
because it doesn't have much heap RAM.
但是，如果你有两倍空闲的内存，
But you know if you're basically if free memories about twice,
你可以买到足够的内存，
you know you could buy enough memory,
空闲内存是活跃内存的两倍，
that free memory twice you know that the live memory,
那么垃圾收集开销不是那么大，在 9% 的范围内。
then the garbage collection overhead is not actually that great, in the 9% range.
所以，要将 GC 开销控制在 10% 以下，
So basically to keep the GC overhead like a rough [] [], around below 10%,
就物理内存而言，你需要大约三倍的堆大小。
you need about three times the heap size in terms of physical memory.
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
我有一个关于写入障碍的问题，
I had a question about the write barriers,
那些是什么，
what are those, do you,
是不是像你说的一些权限？
is it like you said some permissions?
如果你记得之前的课程，
You know, so if you remember the lecture for a little while ago,
那个 Appel&Li 论文，
the kind of Appel&Li paper paper,
在那里，我们讨论了 to 和 from 空间。
where we talked about the to and from spaces.
垃圾收集器运行，
And garbage collector runs,
必须检查指针是否在 from 空间中，
then you have to check whether the pointers in the from space, right,
因为如果它在 form 空间中，你必须复制它。
because it's in the [from] space, you have to copy it.
基本上写入屏障类似，
And basically that the write barrier are very similar,
是同一种类型的想法，
and it's the same sort of type idea,
你需要检查每个指针，
where you need to check every pointer
查看实际指向的空间，
to see you actually actually point in space
垃圾收集器所需要的。
that actually you need in garbage collector.
好的。
Okay.
那就是写入屏障。
That's write barrier.
抱歉，比如空闲内存，
Sorry, so like the free memory,
它是怎么工作的，
what is what is it exactly like how does it work,
在活跃内存大于空闲的情况下。
that the live is more than free.
哦，好的，你买了一些内存，
Oh yeah, yeah, okay so you buy some amount of memory,
而活跃内存是这些 vnode 使用的内存，
and live memory is actually memory that was used by these vnodes,
然后又有 320 兆字节是空闲的。
and then there was another 320 megabyte was just free.
所以，当这个应用程序分配更多 vnode 时，
And so when this application allocated more vnodes,
首先来自空闲内存，
the first came out of the free memory,
直到空闲内存变满，
until the free memory is full,
垃圾收集器同时运行。
[] then concurrently the garbage collector is running.
所以我们的运行方式是三种配置，
And, and so we're running like three configuration,
在一种配置中，空闲内存量是活动内存的两倍，
in one configuration, basically the amount of free memory twice as the live memory,
这意味着垃圾收集器有很多堆内存，
and so that means that the garbage collector has a lot of heap RAM
在与应用程序一起运行的同时执行某种操作。
to do sort of concurrently while running with the application.
如果有很多堆内存，
And if there's a lot of heap RAM,
在这种情况下，是空闲内存，
in this case where free memory,
那么垃圾收集器的开销就没有那么高，
then you know the garbage collection overheads are not that high,
在那里是 10% 左右，而不是 34% 。
over there around 10% instead of 34%.
好的，我知道了，谢谢。
Okay, I see, I see, thank you.
考虑有一些闲置空间，
Think about it like there's a little bit of slack
让垃圾收集器做它的工作。
you know for the garbage collector to do its work.
是的，我以为一共是 320 ，那就太迷惑了。
Right, I I thought that it's like total 320, that was confused.
不，总数是 320 加上 640 ，
No, no, the total is 320 plus 640
并且我的最后一行是 640 加上 1280 。
and my last line is 640 plus 1280.
好的，谢谢。
Okay, thank you.
我要跳过这个，
I'm gonna skip this,
让我稍微说一下关于暂停，
actually let me talk a little bit of pauses,
你知道这是，
you know this is,
Go 垃圾收集器是一个并发垃圾收集器，
the Go garbage collector is a concurrent garbage collector
短暂的暂停让世界停下来很短的一段时间，
and short pauses stop the world for a very short period of time,
用于启用写入障碍，
basically to enable write barriers
然后，应用程序继续运行，
and then basically the application keep on running,
在垃圾收集器不工作的情况下，
while the garbage collector doesn't work,
它是渐进式的，就像我们几周前讨论的那样，
and it's incremental as like the one that we discussed a couple weeks ago,
每个对 new 的调用都会执行一些垃圾收集工作。
where basically every call to new does a little bit of garbage collection work.
所以每次你做一点垃圾收集工作，
And so every time you do a little bit of garbage collection working,
有一些延误，有代价的。
there's some some delay that's been cost, right.
所以我们测量了，
And so we measured you know the,
使用一个应用程序，并查看了最大停顿时间，
it took one application and looked at the maximum pause time,
应用程序可以停止的最长时间，
so the maximum time an application can be stopped
当然垃圾收集器需要做一些工作。
and of course the garbage collector needs to do some work.
结果是最大单次停顿是 150 微秒，
And it turned out to be the max single pause 150 microseconds,
这是使用 TCP 堆栈的 Web 服务器的情况，
that's in the case of the webserver that was using the TCP stack,
基本上 TCP 连接表的很大一部分需要标记，
and basically, a large part of the TCP connection table needed to be marked,
在你继续之前，这花了 115 微秒。
before you know continuing, that took 115 microseconds.
单个 Nginx http 请求的最大总暂停时间是
The maximum total pause time for a single Nginx http request is
单个暂停次数的总和，
the sum of the number of single pauses,
并且单个请求的总最大暂停时间是 582 微秒，
and the maximum pause time in total for a single request was 582 microseconds,
所以当请求进入机器时，
so [] when the request comes into the machine,
在总共有 582 微秒延迟，执行该请求。
during you know there was total delay of 582 microseconds, execute that request.
而且这种情况非常罕见，
And it just happened very, very seldom,
只有 3% 的请求时间延迟超过 100 微秒。
you know only you know point 3% requested times actually had a delay of more than 100 microseconds.
所以这并不好，
And so you know that's not good,
如果你想要实现一个 SLA ，
if you're trying to achieve like an SLA
或者请求的最长时间很小，
or where basically the longest period of time of request takes you know it's small,
但是你查看谷歌的 Tail at Scale 的论文，
but you know the, you look at you know google papers about like tail at scale,
比如最长的请求需要多长时间，
like how long the longest request takes,
他们谈论的是
you know they're talking about
几十毫秒，毫秒或 10 毫秒的量级，
the order of tens of milliseconds, milliseconds or 10 milliseconds,
所以这些程序有最大暂停，
and so probably the programs that these particular programs that actually have a pause
最大的暂停是 582 微秒，
with maximum [] to pause for 582 microseconds,
在预算之内。
sort of within the budget.
这不是很理想，但也不疯狂，
You know it's not ideal, but it's not crazy,
所以基本上说，
and so basically says that actually the,
这基本上说明，
really, what this basically says that,
Go 设计者做得非常好，
the Go designers you know did actually terribly good job
在实现垃圾收集器方面，
of actually implementing their garbage collector,
或者令人印象深刻的工作。
or impressively good job.
这是我们在做这个项目时注意到的一件事，
And this is one of those things that we've noticed while doing this project,
每次我们升级 Go 运行时，
every time we upgraded the Go runtime,
下一个运行时，带来了更好的垃圾收集器，
the next runtime, it came with a better garbage collector,
这些数字变得越来越好。
and actually these numbers got better and better.
好的，我想再说一个技术细节，
Okay, one more through technical detail that I want to go over,
到目前为止， Linux 和 Biscuit 之间的第一个比较，
so far you know like the first comparison between Linux and Biscuit,
这并不公平，
you know it's not really fair,
因为 Biscuit 和 Linux 实现的功能略有不同，
because Biscuit and Linux implement slightly different features,
所以我们又做了一个实验，
so we did one more experiment,
我们尝试编写两个完全相同的内核路径，
where we basically tried to code up two kernel paths completely identical,
在 Linux 和类似的 C 和 Go 中，
evolving in Linux and in like in C and Go,
所以，我们看了代码路径，并对其进行验证，
and so we looked at the code path and sort of verify it,
基本上它实现的是完全相同的东西，
basically you know it implements exactly the same thing,
我们看一下汇编结构，
and we look at the assembly structures,
来真正了解它们的不同之处，
you know to really see what what the differences are,
会有一些不同，
there gonna be some differences,
因为 Go 要支付安全检查，
because Go is going to pay the safety checks,
但就基本操作而言，
but just in terms of basic operation,
至少两个代码路径在功能方面是相同的。
that at least two code paths are identical in terms of functionality.
我们对两条代码路径都这样做了，
And we did that for two code paths,
这很难做到，
you know it's difficult to do,
因为这是辛苦的工作，
because it's painstaking job,
我们做了两个，
we did for two,
或者 Cody 做了两个。
or Cody did actually for two.
然后我们对它们进行比较，
And then we compare them,
这是其中一个结果，
and so here's results from one of them,
这是管道 ping-pong 测试，
this is pipe ping-pong you know sort of test,
ping-pong 字节在管道上通过，
you know ping-pong you know byte across a pipe,
我们查看了通过内核的代码路径，
and we just looked at the code path through the kernel
让字节从管道的一端到管道的另一端。
to actually get a byte from one end to the pipe to the other end of the pipe.
Go 中的代码有 1.2k 行，
You know, sort of amount code in Go is like this 1.2k lines code
而 C 是 1.8k 行代码，
and C it's 1.8k lines of code,
而且没有分配，没有 GC ，
and there's no allocation, no GC,
所以这些东西是不同之处，
so those things are just a differ,
我们还研究了运行时，
we also looked at runtime,
比如在两个代码路径中花费的时间最多的地方，
like where's the most time spent in both code paths,
同样的前十大指令出现了，
you know the same top-10 instructions showed up,
所以我们有信心，代码路径真的很近，
so we have some confidence that the code paths really are closer,
近到可以让它们相似。
closer, you can get to make them similar.
然后我们看一下每秒可以完成的操作量，
And then we looked at basically the amount of operations you can do per second,
正如你在这里看到的，
and as you see here,
Go 比 C 实现慢一点，
basically you know Go a little slower than the C implementation
大约慢了 1.15% 。
and you know the ratio is about 1.15% slower.
你看一下 prologue/safety-check ，
And, that's you know you look at the prologue/safety-checks,
这些都是 C 代码不需要执行的指令，
you know these are all the instructions that C code does not have to execute,
结果是汇编指令多了 16% ，
it turned out to be 16% more assembly instructions,
所以这大概是有道理的。
and so that's sort of roughly sort of makes sense.
所以主要结论是 Go 会更慢，
So you know the main conclusion is you know Go is slower,
但是很有竞争性，不是慢得离谱。
but pretty competitive, you know not not ridiculously slower.
这似乎与之前的结果是一样的，
And that seems in line with the early results of
我们直接将 Linux 与 Biscuit 进行比较。
where we did these Linux to Biscuit comparison directly.
好的，让我放大更多一点，
Okay, so let me zoom a little bit further,
让我跳过这个，
let me skip this,
因为我想稍微谈一下，
because I want to talk a little bit about,
我们一开始问的这类问题，
this sort of the question that we asked in the beginning,
是否应该对新内核使用高级语言。
where should one use high-level language for a new kernel.
也许，不是直接回答，
And, maybe you know like instead of answering,
在这张幻灯片里，我有一些想法，
I have some thoughts about this here in this slide,
我们得出了一些结论，
you know there were some conclusion that we draw,
这不是一个明确的结论，一些考虑，
and you know it's not a crisp conclusion, some considerations,
所以也许我们应该退后一步，问问自己这个问题，
so maybe to take a step back and ask yourself the question,
比如你喜欢什么，
like what would you have preferred,
你是更喜欢用 C 语言编写 xv6 和实验，
you know, would you have preferred to write you know xv6 and the labs in C
还是更喜欢使用类似 Go 的高级语言。
or would you prefer to use a high-level language for example like Go.
特别是回答这个问题，
And particularly answer this question,
你会避免什么样的 bug ，
what what kind of bugs would you have avoided,
也许你在这节课中有一些时间
and maybe you have some time during this lecture
来思考一下你有什么 bug ，
to think about like what bugs you had,
我很想听到你的经历，
and I would love to hear you know what your experience,
你认为切换到高级语言
how do you think switching to a high level language
会如何改变你的经历。
would have changed your experience.
或者你这个问题有任何想法。
Or if you have any thoughts on this question at all.
让我暂停一会，
Let me, pause you for a little bit,
你可以考虑一下，再加入进来。
so you can think about this and maybe chime in.
我有过几次这样做的经历，
I have had a couple of times when I did the thing,
我在函数中创建对象，
where I create an object in a function
然后返回指向该对象的指针，
and then return a pointer to it
然后我用指针做一些事情，
and then I do stuff with a pointer
然后我意识到这个物体不见了。
and then I realized that the object is gone.
是的，这是一个典型的释放后使用的例子。
Yeah, so this is a classic example of sort of use-after-free case, correct.
是的，第二次我比第一次更快地意识到了这一点。
Yeah, the second time I realize it faster than the first time.
是的，这绝对是真的，
Yeah, it's definitely true,
当你看到几次这些 bug ，
when you see a couple of times in those bugs,
你可以做得更好。
here you get better at them.
还有任何关于这个的其他想法吗，
Any other thoughts on this,
人们有过什么样的经历。
you know what the experience that people have had.
想想你最坏的 bug ，花了最多时间的 bug ，
Think about your worst bugs, bugs that took most time,
高级语言会有帮助吗？
would high-level language would have help?
我觉得有些 bug 确实很难对付，
I think it definitely like like some of the bugs were absolutely terrible to deal with,
但同时，就像在这个上下文中，
but at the same time like in in this context,
我非常感谢能够使用如此低级的 C 语言，
I definitely appreciated having to work with such a low-level language C,
因为它帮助我获得，
because it helped me to really gain a very,
对操作系统内部的情况有了非常深刻的了解，
a deep understanding of what's actually going on inside the operating system,
比如它是如何处理内存的，
like how it's working with memory,
它绝对是新的，
like it it it's definitely refreshing to to
不把所有的东西都抽象化，
like not have all of that abstracted away
真正看到到底发生了什么。
and to actually see exactly what's going on.
是啊，这很有道理，
Yeah, it makes a lot of sense,
还有其他任何人对此有意见吗？
any other, any other people have opinions on this?
我想也有很多 bug ，
I think also made a lot of bugs
在我在字符串末尾或类似的地方写入的时候，
in which I was writing after the end of string or something like that,
但是我没有得到任何有用的反馈，
but then I wasn't getting any useful feedback about it
然后我无法解释的非常奇怪的事情发生了，
and then very strange things happened, that I couldn't explain,
所以，是的，我。
so yeah, I.
那出现在实验一中，
That show up in lab one,
那里有很多奇怪的操作，
where there's a bunch of strange operations,
比如当你解析目录之类的东西的时候。
like when you parsing directories and things like that.
它出现在多个应用程序中。
It showed up in multiple apps.
好的，我并不惊讶。
Okay, I'm not surprised.
好的，这是一个很好的例子，
Okay, that's a great example,
拥有真正的字符串对象是非常好的。
like you know that it's very nice to actually have real string objects.
我想说的是，
Something on my end is that,
我发现缺少映射之类的东西，
I I found myself lacking whenever I needed something like a map,
每次我需要做 for 循环，然后查找。
and I just I I [] every time I needed to do for loop over something and then find.
是的。
Yeah.
不过，我要说的是，
However, I will say,
来自高级编程背景，
like coming from a high-level programming background,
这是我第一次真正接触到像 C 这样的东西，
this was my first real exposure to something like C,
所以跟 Noah 的观点一样，
so going of of Noah's point,
它在某种程度上帮助我理解了，
it kind of helped me to understand
这意味着什么，
really what it means that,
我正在编写的代码是在 CPU 上运行的，
this code that I'm writing is actually running on the CPU
一切都是从 CPU 的角度出发的。
and everything is from the perspective of the CPU.
是的，还有其他想法吗？
Yep, any other thoughts?
哦，我记得具体是，
Oh, I actually remember it was specifically,
安全字符串复制和字符串复制的区别，
the difference between safe string copy or just string copy,
其中一个使用空终止符，
one of them was putting, was using the null terminator,
那就是。
and that was.
是的，一个常见的 C bug 。
Yeah, a common C bug.
好吧，第一件事是谢谢你的投入，
Well, so you know first thing you know, thanks for the input,
当然，我们不会将 xv6 更改为 Go
of course we're not going to change xv6 to Go
或任何高级语言，
or any high-level language exactly,
因为 Noah 和 Amir 提到的原因，
for the reasons that you know have a number of you like Noah, Amir mentioned,
Go 隐藏的太多了，
Go still hides too much,
在这个课程中，
and you know in this particular class,
整个目的是试图理解所有事情，
whole purpose is really trying to understand everything
在 CPU 和系统调用接口之间，
between the CPU and the system call interface,
比如， Go 隐藏了线程，
and for example Go of course hides threads,
你知道我们不想隐藏它，
and you know we don't want to hide that,
我们想向你解释线程是如何实现的，
we want to explain to you actually how threads are implemented,
所以，我们不想对你隐藏这个。
and so, we would not want to hide this from you.
所以可以肯定的是，未来几年，
So certainly future years,
xv6 课程将继续使用 C ，
you know of xv6 class will keep on using C,
但是如果你实现一个新的内核，
but if you implement a new kernel
你的目标不是教育学生关于内核的知识，
and goal is not you know educating students about kernels,
但目标是安全的，高性能的内核，
but goals are I'd like to say safe, you know high performance kernel,
你可以从这项研究中得出一些结论，
you know there's sort of you know somethings you conclude from this study,
他们做了什么，我们做了什么。
they've done and what we've done, right.
是的，内存或性能是最重要的，
Yeah, memory or performance is really paramount,
你不能牺牲 15% ，那么你应该使用 C ，
you know you can't sacrifice 15%, then you should probably use C,
如果你想最大限度地减少内存使用，也应该使用 C 。
if you want to minimize memory use, you probably use C too.
如果安全很重要，
If safety is important or security is important
也许高级语言就是我们要走的路。
and probably the high-level language is the way to go.
也许在许多情况下，性能是重要的，而不是绝对的，
And probably in many cases performances merely important as opposed to absolute paramount,
在很多情况下，
and in many case,
我认为使用高级语言做内核是非常合理的事情。
I think you know using high-level languages perfectly reasonable thing to do for kernel.
也许我学到了一件事，
Probably one thing I've learned,
也许 Cody Robert 和我从整个项目中学到的是，
probably you know Cody Robert and I learned from this whole project is
任何编程语言都是编程语言，
like whatever programming language is a programming language,
你可以用它来构建内核，
and you can use it to build kernels,
你可以构建用户应用程序，
you can build user applications,
在某种程度上，这并不是什么真正的阻碍。
there's not really standing anything in really in a way.
好的，我觉得该结束了，
Okay, you know I think it's time to wrap up,
如果你还有什么问题，
you know if you have any more questions,
可以随意停留并提问，
you know fell free to hang around and ask them,
如果你要去别的地方，
if you have to go somewhere else,
祝你顺利完成 mmap 实验，
good luck with finishing the mmap lab,
对于你们，
and for those of you,
当我们要离开校园过感恩节的人来说，
when we have to are leaving campus for Thanksgiving,
一路顺风，希望感恩节过后见到你，
safe travels and hope to see you after Thanksgiving
在感恩节后的周一的课程中。
in Monday's lecture after Thanksgiving.
谢谢。
Thank you.
我很好奇，你是怎么实现的，
I was curious, how did you implement it,
上面说你在在硬件上做这个，
it said you are doing that just on the hardware,
所以当你开始的时候，你是怎么开始的。
so like when you start out, how do you start out.
这里有很少的垫片代码，
You know there's basically little shim code,
它对硬件做足够的设置，
that sets up enough of the hardware,
当 Biscuit 请求，
so that when Biscuit you know asks for,
当 Go 运行时请求堆的内存时，
when the Go runtime ask for memory for the heap,
我们可以响应。
that we can actually respond.
这是 Go 运行时所依赖的主要内容之一。
That was one of the main things that actually Go runtime actually relies on.
是的，我想你说的是，
Right, I guess I was like you said that,
你没有使用虚拟机，所以。
you didn't use a virtual machine for that, so.
我们用了，当然大部分开发都在 QEMU 上，
We did, of course we developed most of development on QEMU
当然，我们还必须让它在硬件上运行，
and of course again we actually have to get it running on the hardware,
这也要解决一堆问题，
that also costs there's a bunch of problems,
因为引导加载程序不同，
because the boot loaders are different,
需要编写一系列引导代码，
there's a bunch of boot code that you actually need to write,
如果你在 QEMU 上运行就不用写了，
you don't have to write if you run it on QEMU,
诸如此类的东西，
and that kind of stuff,
但是大部分的开发都是在 QEMU 上完成的，
but most of the development is all done on QEMU,
事实上，如果你想在 QEMU 上运行 Biscuit ，
in fact if you want to actually show you running Biscuit on QEMU,
它看起来非常简单，类似 xv6 ，
and it looks very simple to xv6,
它唯一就是显示提示符，
you know the only thing it does like show prompt,
没有窗口系统，什么都没有。
there's no window system, nothing like that.
好的，我明白了，
Okay, I see,
所以如果你在引导代码中犯了错误，会发生什么情况。
so like what happens if you if you make a mistake in the boot code.
它不能启动，
It doesn't boot,
基本上什么都没发生，
you know basically nothing happens,
完全没什么东西。
you know it's completely nothing.
你怎么知道？
How do you know?
你会知道的，
You, you, you will know,
因为你知道，因为你看不到打印的语句，
because you know okay what will happen is because you don't see print statement,
比如 xv6 ，我们打印的第一件事是，
like xv6 for the first thing we print is
比如 xv6 hello 或者 xv6 引导，
like you know xv6 hello or something or xv6 booting,
你不会看到这样的东西，
you won't see anything like that,
所以你什么也看不到，
and so you'll see nothing,
然后你必须追踪，并猜测问题可能出在哪里。
and then you'll have to track down and guess what the problem might be.
好的，那你是通过查看吗？
Okay, so you do it by looking?
好的，你可以向 UART 同步写一个，
Okay, little bit, you can write a [synchronously] to the UART,
你可以比如，
you know you could like,
你看到的字符，把它们放在代码中的随机位置，
you know characters you see put them in random places in the code,
希望你能看到一些东西。
and hope that you see something.
这很有趣，谢谢。
This is interesting, thank you.
你知道。
You know.
我想问一下，
I wanted to ask,
当你，我知道你实现 Go ，
when you, so I know like you implemented the Go,
有一些调用 Go 进行时会创建，
some of the calls that Go runtime would make,
有一些无法创建，
that you cannot make,
因为你正在实现内核本身，
because you're implementing the kernel itself,
有没有类似的，
is there any like,
你是不是使用汇编实现了，
did you just implement just all of that in assembly
或者这些也可以使用 Go 来实现，
or did you say okay like some of this we can still do in Go,
比如我们可以让 Go 走地更近一点，
like we can bring Go a bit closer,
然后汇编只做需要的事情，
and then do assembly only what's necessary,
你说的，一旦 Go 运行时结束，就是汇编？
what did you say like once the Go runtime ends like that's assembly.
这就是 1500 行汇编的来源，
You the that's where the 1500 lines of assembly came from,
在 Biscuit 中，
in the, in Biscuit,
这基本上就是代码，
you know that is basically the code
为运行 Go 运行时做好准备。
to sort of get everything ready to be actually able to run the Go runtime.
其中一些我们可以使用 C 实现，
Now some of that we would have implemented C,
但我们不想这样做，
but we didn't want to do that,
因为我们不想使用任何 C 语言，
because we didn't want to use any C,
所以我们使用汇编。
so we're use assembly.
其中许多需要汇编，
And many of it actually required assembly,
因为它在引导部分。
because it's in the booting part.
是的，但我想有些部分，不是引导，
Right, but I guess some of the part, that's not the boot,
我知道有些你不能避免一些引导代码和汇编，
so I I you know I know that some just you cannot avoid some boot code and assembly,
但是你能不能把一些汇编改为 Go ，
but could you, could you have transformed some of the assembly to Go,
还是你做了[]。
or did you go to the [].
我们做了很多 Go ，
We did a bunch of Go,
是在很早的时候就开始了，
that basically runs very early on,
有些 Go 非常小心，
you know some of the Go goes quite careful,
它不进行任何内存分配，
it doesn't do any memory allocation,
我们试着尽可能多地使用 Go ，
and we tried to write as much as possible Go,
我必须看代码，
I I can like I have to look at the code exactly
才能回答你的问题，
you know to be able to answer your question,
具体地说，你可以看看 git repo ，
specifically you can look at the git repo,
但是，是的，我们试着使用 Go 写所有的东西。
but, yeah, we tried to write everything in Go.
然后我有一个不相干的小问题，
And then one like kind of unrelated small question I had,
Go 协程是怎么做的，
what does Go do with its Go routines,
使它可以运行成百上千的 Go 协程，
that makes it possible to run like hundred thousands of them,
因为你不能起成百上千个个线程。
because you cannot just spin up a hundred thousand pthreads, right.
是的，这要看情况，
Yeah, it depends,
时间很长，
a lot longer
所以主要的问题是你需要分配堆栈，
and so the main issue is that you need to allocate stack,
而 Go 运行时会递增地分配堆栈，
and the Go runtime actually allocates stack incrementally
随着你运行 Go 协程，它们会动态增长，
and so grows them dynamically as you run your Go Go routine,
这是 prologue 代码的作用，
this where's prologue code is for,
当你进行函数调用时，
when you make a function call,
你会查看是否有足够的空间
you see if there's enough space
来进行函数调用，
to actually make the function call,
如果没有，它将为你动态增长。
and if not, it will grow dynamically for you.
通常在 pthread 实现中，
And often in pthread implementations,
分配线程是更重量级的，
allocating threads a little bit more heavyweight,
因为，比如 Linux 对应，
because actually for example Linux basically corresponds
对应的内核线程也要被分配，
corresponding kernel threads is actually allocated too,
它们往往更重量级。
and they tend to be more heavyweight than.
我明白了,
I see,
Go 协程的调度是否完全在用户空间中完成的，
is the is the scheduling of all the Go routines done completely in user space,
或者它帮助自己使用一些内核。
or does it help itself with some of kernel, so.
它主要是在用户空间中完成的。
It is mostly done in user space.
所以 Go 运行时分配了一堆内核线程，
So the Go runtime allocates a bunch of kernel threads,
他们把它们叫做 mthreads ，
you know they call them I think mthreads,
在这之上，它实现了 Go 协程。
and on top of that it implements the Go routines.
所以它有几个内核线程，
So it's so it has, like a couple kernel threads
它共享给所有的 Go 协程，基于正在运行的。
that it shares to all Go routines based on which ones running.
是的。
Yes.
哦，理解了，是的。
Oh, that makes sense, yeah.
有没有类似的 C 或 C++ 的等价物，
Is there like any C C++ equivalent,
比如，你能不能做这样的事来节省内存。
like, could you could you do something like that to save to save some memory.
是的，人们已经做到了，可以管理高性能，
Yeah people have done, you know able to manage like high performance,
C 库是线程库，
you know so C libraries are thread libraries,
你可以为数以百万计的线程创建数以千计的线程，
that way you can create thousands of you know threads for millions of threads,
使用类似的方式。
you know do a similar style.
好了，你们好好休息，我得走了。
Okay, you guys have a good break, I must head out.
你也是。
You too.
下周或下两周见。
See you next week or two weeks.
是的，哦。
Yeah, oh.
哦，请继续。
Oh, go ahead.
抱歉，我有一个关于垫片的基本问题，
I'm sorry, so I have a maybe basic question about the shims
我想我可能，
and I guess I think also maybe,
还不太熟悉运行库是什么样子，
I'm just not familiar with kind of specifically what like a runtime is
我猜我的疑惑来自这一事实，
and I guess like my confusion comes from the fact,
比如，在裸机器上 xv6 和 C 如何工作的，
that like from a metal model of how xv6 and C works,
C 是一种编译语言，
is that C compiles C is a compiled language
所以它直接进入汇编或机器代码，
and so it goes directly to assembly or machine code,
所以它像是在 CPU 上运行，
and so it kind of just runs on the CPU,
所以我想，
and so I guess,
就像 xv6 操作系统不需要垫片程序一样，
like there is no need for a shim for like xv6 OS,
但我想 Go 也是一种编译语言，
but I guess my understanding is Go is also a compiled language,
所以也会变成汇编语言，
so it also goes to the assembly,
那么为什么在这种情况下需要垫片，
so why is there a need for like a shim in this case,
xv6 是否有这样的垫片，
why, why is there maybe is a shim for like xv6,
或者这里有什么不同，
or you know what, what is different here
为什么有些事情不能只在 CPU 上做。
and why are there, why are there things that can't just be done on the CPU.
是的，一个很好的问题，
Yeah yeah, a great question,
所以我想你问题的答案是，
so I think the answer to your question is that,
Go 运行时提供了所有类型的功能，
the Go runtime provides all kinds of features,
比如你没有的，
that like you know you don't have, right,
当你在 xv6 中运行 C 的时候，
in running when you're running C in xv6,
所以 Go 运行时提供线程，
so Go runtime provides threads,
Go 运行时提供调度器，
Go runtime provides scheduler,
Go 运行时提供哈希表，
Go runtime provides hash tables,
Go 运行时提供垃圾收集器，
Go runtime provides garbage collector,
这需要在运行时运行，
that actually needs to run at runtime, right,
而在 xv6 中没有垃圾收集器，
then there's no garbage collector in xv6,
并且我们实现了线程，
and we implement the threads,
比如，为了支持垃圾收集器，
and for example to support the garbage collector,
它需要一个堆来分配内存，
it needs a heap you know for to allocate memory from,
所以访问底层的操作系统，
and so like ask the operating system underlying operating system,
请给我一些内存，
so please give me you know some memories,
我可以把它当作堆使用。
that I can use it as a heap.
基本上垫片层实现了这些功能，
And basically the shim layer implements exactly so that kind of functionality,
Go 运行时在运行时要做的工作。
that the Go runtime needs to do a job at runtime.
我明白。
I see.
是的，你说得有点道理，
Yeah, you have a slightly makes sense,
我还有一个后续问题，
I actually a follow-up question is,
也许这是一个愚蠢的问题，
maybe this is a dumb question,
比如我们能不能编译运行时到机器代码，或者。
but like like can we just compile to runtime down to machine code, or.
运行时被编译为运行。
Runtime is compile to run.
好的。
Okay.
运行库本身也是编译的，
It goes like you know the runtime itself is also compiled,
但这是程序的一部分，
but it's like you're part of the program
在运行 Go 代码时需要一直运行。
that needs to run always running run Go code.
它必须在那里，
It has to be there,
就像 C 也有一个很小的运行时，
like even like C has a small runtime,
如果你想一想，我们有 printf ，
if you think about you know we have like printf
是 C 运行时的一部分，
is part of should live to C runtime,
字符串操作是 C 运行时的一部分，
string operations are part of the C runtime, right,
它们也是编译的，
they're compile too,
但是 C 运行时有一些很少的函数，
but there's a bunch of small number of functions that the C runtime has,
但是它们的运行时太小了，跟 Go 运行时比起来，
but their runtime is so small compared to the Go runtime,
支持更多的功能，
that you know have to support many more features,
因为 Go 程序依赖于它们。
because of you know programs Go programs rely on them.
我明白了，我明白了，
I see, I see,
我想最后一个问题可能是这样的，
and I guess the last question would maybe be like,
在这种情况下，是不是有点像，
is it it kind of sounds like that in this case,
Go 运行时或这种情况下的垫片程序
the Go runtime or like the actually the shim in this case
承担了一些常用功能，
is almost taking on some of the functionality normally,
就像它几乎就像一个小的，
like it's almost like it's like a mini,
它就像一个小的操作系统层，
it's almost kind of like, it's like a mini OS layer,
就像它是另一层，
like in terms that it's just like another layer
执行一些低级系统功能。
that's performing some low-level system functionality, like reasonable.
是的，你可以，
Yeah you can,
也许可以用一种方式来考虑 xv6 ，
maybe one way to think about xv6,
它也有一个非常非常小的垫片，
it also has a very very minimal shim,
也许当引导的时候，
you know maybe like when the boots correct,
它做的第一件事就是分配一些堆栈，
the first thing it does actually allocates some stack,
就可以调用 C 主函数了。
so that you can actually call the C main function.
你可以考虑一下这段代码，
And you can think about that little fragment of code
它只有几个语句，
which is only a couple statements,
就是 xv6 的垫片层。
the shim layer for xv6.
一旦你通过了几个指令，
And once you know you're through a couple of instructions,
你到达 C 代码，一切都很好。
you're actually C code and everything is fine.
Go 运行时的垫片层稍微大一些，
And you know the shim layer to Go runtime is slightly bigger,
因为还有更多的功能需要设置，
because there's a bunch of more features that need to be set up,
在 Go 运行时执行之前。
before the Go runtime actually happily execute.
好的，这很有帮助，很有道理，酷。
Okay, yeah that's helpful, that makes sense, cool.
谢谢。
Thank you.
不用谢。
You're welcome.
感恩节快乐。
Happy Thanksgiving.
是的，你也是。
Yeah, you too.
哦，我有个关于 ping-pong 程序的问题忘了问，
Oh, I had a question about the ping-pong program that I forgot to ask,
我记得我们在一个实验中也做了一个 ping-pong 程序。
so I remember we also did a ping-pong program in one of the labs.
那不是一百，一千行代码，为什么是。
It was not a hundred, those a thousand lines of code, why is.
因为，第一，我想你说的是实验一，
Because like one, I think you're referring to a lab one,
你做了 ping-pong 让一个字节通过管道。
you do the ping-pong with a byte across the pipe.
是的。
Yeah.
好的，那是用户空间的基准测试，
Okay, so that's the user side of the benchmark,
内核方面是另一面，
the kernel side correctly is the other side of it,
我们所做的是，
and basically you know that what we did is
实现以相同方式传递的内核。
implement the kernel passed in identical manner.
好的。
Okay.
所以在执行系统调用，
So like you know you executing the start the system call,
使用堆栈帧中的变量，
using variables in the stack frame,
调用查看管道，
you know calling into looking up the pipe,
然后可能会运行调度程序来唤醒接收者，
you know then running maybe the scheduler to wake up you know the receiver
那是整个代码路径，
and that whole code path,
在内核方面，我们试图实现它，
you know on the kernel side, we tried to implement it,
在 C 和 Go 中是一样的。
identically in C and in Go.
好的，我明白了。
Okay,I see.
但基准与你的基准一样，
But the benchmark is basically the same as your benchmark,
你在实验一中实现的，
that you implemented actually in lab one,
它的用户级别方面。
the user level side of it.
好的，这就说得通了，
Right, right, okay that makes sense,
所以，那是不是意味着，
so, so does that mean like,
我的意思是，如果在 xv6 中这样做，
I mean I think that if you do that in xv6
将大大少于 1000 行代码，
would be significantly less than a thousand lines of code,
如果你愿意，使用所有内核代码。
if you like take all the kernel code.
这里有上千行的汇编指令，
There's thousand thousand lines for assembly instructions correct,
我不知道，我必须看一下，
so you know I I don't know I will have to look at,
但你会用到 trapframe 代码，
but you know you're gonna use the trapframe code,
系统调用调度，
you know syscall dispatch,
到 fd 层，文件描述符，
going to the the fd layer, correct, the file descriptors,
然后是一小段管道代码，
then a little bit of pipe code,
然后是 copyin 和 copyout ，
then copyin and copyout,
然后是调度器，
then the scheduler
然后再次跳出或返回。
and then basically all [] and then bailing out again or returning.
是的，好的，这就说得通了。
Yeah, okay, that make sence.
我不知道怎么表示脑中的代码，
I don't know how to talk my head on my client what code is,
但是你知道。
but you know.